<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses next to God, and Aaron next to Moses subordinate and subservient opened in a sermon preached at St. Peters in Exon on Wednesday the 29th of May 1661, being the solemn and anniversary thanksgiving for the double birth of our most gracious sovereign, K. Charles the II / by John Copleston ...</title>
            <author>Copleston, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19720146</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19720146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1698:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses next to God, and Aaron next to Moses subordinate and subservient opened in a sermon preached at St. Peters in Exon on Wednesday the 29th of May 1661, being the solemn and anniversary thanksgiving for the double birth of our most gracious sovereign, K. Charles the II / by John Copleston ...</title>
                  <author>Copleston, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid for Richard Thrale, and are to be sold at the Cross Keys in St. Paul's Church-yard at the entring into Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LXI [1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Pslams LXXVII, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOSES next to GOD, <hi>AND</hi> AARON next to MOSES <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BORDINATE</hi> and <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BSERVIENT:</hi> Opened, in A SERMON <hi>PREACHED</hi> At St. PETERS in EXON on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1661. being the Solemn and Anniverſary Thankſgiving, for the double Birth of our moſt Gracious <hi>SOVERAIGN</hi> K. Charles the II.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Copleſton</hi> M. A. ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Kings Coll.</hi> in <hi>Camb.</hi> now Vicar of <hi>Broad Clyſte</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and Prebend of St. <hi>Peters Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 2.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I exhort therefore, that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men: for Kings, and for all that are in authority.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieron</hi> Epiſt. ad Evagr. <hi>58.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Aaron <hi>&amp; filii ſummi Sacerdotes, &amp; ut</hi> Aaron Eleazar <hi>&amp; Levitae, juxta traditiones Apoſtolicas hoc ſunt Epiſcopi, Presbyteri, &amp; Diaconi.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W Godbid</hi> for <hi>Richard Thrale,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Croſs Keys</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard at the entring into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> MDCLXI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. COPLESTON BAMPFEILD, Bar<hi rend="sub">t</hi>. High Sheriff of the County of <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I have good reaſon to acknowledge with all thankfulneſs, the conſtancy of that affection and favour you have ever had for me; yet I muſt aſſure you, and all the world, the arguments which prevailed with me for this Dedication, were fetch'd from a Topick of a far different nature. The diſcourſe is of Publick concerment, and therefore no Patron could be more ſuitable then one of ſo publick a ſpirit, as all that know you muſt bear witneſs unto; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> will not go out under any other Patronage, ſave of ſo Loyal a ſubject, and hearty a well-wiſher to the Doctrine and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of our Church: I mean, that good old way eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, practiſed by our Anceſtors ever ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſealed with the blood of Martyrs, which is too evident to be denied or eluded; unleſs it can be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Cranmer</hi> were no Epiſcopal men. Nor do I doubt of your candid acceptance, having been privy to that cheerful reſolution and undaunted courage, with which you undertook, though with the hazard of all that was dear
<pb facs="tcp:109337:3"/> unto you, to endevour to make way for the Celebration of ſuch a day, and a Sermon of ſuch a ſubject upon it; in a time of the greateſt difficulty, when the enemies both of Church and State, God and their King, were moſt preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and many people began to be content they ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>Their brawny necks being now accuſtomed to the Yoke, with <hi>Iſſachar</hi> they couched down between their burdens; the reaſon whereof is alſo rendred in the ſame pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, <hi>Gen. 49.15. He ſaw that reſt was good, and the land that it was pleaſant, and bowed his ſhoulder to bear, and became a ſervant unto tribute.</hi> But God was pleaſed to defeat thoſe reſolutions, and to ſtrangle as Loyal Deſigns, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Intendments, as ever were in the world; making them to become abortive in their very birth; yet with a far greater deſign of mercy, then if your intentions had come into Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and every action b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en crowned with its deſired ſucceſs; for your way muſt have been through that Red-ſea, on the brinks whereof your feet then ſtood, and perhaps when you had paſſed through that, you might have ſeen a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs before you. But God has brought us to <hi>Canaan</hi> a nearer, and much a ſafer way, giving us the Land of Promiſe, without acquainting us at all, either with the Red-ſea or Wilderneſs: And all this, that his own Counſels might take place, and that ſuch a Deliverance might be the more wonderful in our eyes, when we were thus convinced that it was his doing.</p>
            <p>But though you were prevented from laying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb facs="tcp:109337:3"/> as you intended, yet you reſolved to contribute your utmoſt, for the finiſhing that in the Weſt, which was ſo happily began in the North; witneſs the indefatigable pains you took, and the great charges you were at, that things might not roul back again, when they were once tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, though as yet very hazardous. What acceptance your labour and travail found with all perſons of Honour and Loyalty in theſe parts, is not unknown to any that then knew the Weſt.</p>
            <p>Nor did thoſe Buds and Bloſſomes of Loyalty and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to His <hi>Moſt Sacred Majeſty,</hi> onely put forth when it was now the ſpring, and the ſummer of our deliverance drew nigh; but bore fruit even in the midſt of that ſad winter, when the blackeſt ſtorm was over us. How you were afflicted all along with all them that ſuffered upon the account of the King, or the Church, or both? How their iron even entred into your ſoul, thoſe ſeaſonable Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which paſſed through my hands, for refreſhing the bowels of ſuch afflicted ones, can teſtifie; theſe are I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe good grounds for publiſhing it under your name. There was great reaſon for that, ſure, if I might with modeſty publiſh any thing at all, after ſo many Exquiſite Sermons, and Treatiſes already Extant upon this ſubject; for this I ſhall wave the ordinary excuſes, though I could with much evidence of truth have alledged them all, and only ſay for my ſelf, that when of old the Arke was to be adorned, though men of the greateſt abilities brought Gold, Silver, and Purple; yet were not thoſe of meaner quality to
<pb facs="tcp:109337:4"/> be rejected, who appeared with an offering, though but of Badgers-skins, or Goats-hair. Printing is not my itch as they can bear me witneſs, who are privy to the temptations I have often had unto it, and hitherto ever reſiſted, though the authority of ſome very excellent perſons, together with other weighty reaſons have now prevailed upon me.</p>
            <p>I hope, no man will like it the worſe, for coming a little otherwiſe from the Preſs, then it was uttered from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; the Eye and the Ear, the Phancy and the Judgment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very different, what the one is affected with, the other without ſome corrective may nauſeat. Beſides, I have here laid down the ſubſtance of the matter all a long, as it was then delivered, though in ſome places (as it fell out) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where contracted, in others a little more enlarged, where the ſubject might better have been ſtreched out to the length of a voluminous Chronicle, then confined within the narrow bounds of a Sermon. A Paragraph or two I have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed, <hi>De novo,</hi> Word for word out of Mr. <hi>Dud. Diggs,</hi> for ſatisfaction of ſuch who ſtill perſiſt in very great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, only upon the pretence of thoſe convictions they lye under, from the no grounds of a falſly fancied Co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, whereby every unprejudiced Reader may in ſome ſort be ſatisfied, others will never.</p>
            <p>I ſhall hold you no longer in the porch, then only to let you know, that as I long have, ſo ſhall daily bow my Knees to the Father of Spirits, that he would bleſs and guide you in all your undertakings, that your ancient Family which has f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſo many years been in honour in theſe parts, never
<pb facs="tcp:109337:4"/> ſuffer any Eclipſe or Diminution, but that you may ever be followed with freſh accruements of temporal Honour here, and ſo walk as to obtain an Eternal weight of Glory hereafter; which ſhall ever be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged and devoted Servant, JOHN COPLESTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:5"/>
            <head>MOSES next to GOD, AND AARON next to MOSES, <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BORDINATE</hi> &amp; S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BSERVIENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM 77.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou leadeſt thy People like a flock, by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Mitting what might be ſpoken, touching either the Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Occaſion of this Pſalme; I ſhall betake my ſelf to the ſubject matter, in which he that runs may read Faiths Conflict and Triumph.</p>
            <p>In the firſt whereof, we have the afflicted Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Perſon of the Prophet <hi>Aſaph,</hi> ſtrangely ſtrugling with fits of Diffidence and Diſtruſt of God; whilſt he compares their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proſperous condition, with their preſent ſad preſſures under <hi>Pharaoh Neco,</hi> or elſe the Babyloniſh Yoak: Thoſe dayes wherein they injoyed their God, in the daily ſervices of the Temple, (for ſo <hi>Cajetane</hi> underſtands thoſe Songs of <hi>Sion</hi> in the Night <hi>v.</hi> 6. with the years of their Captivity, wherein their neglected Harps were hung upon the Willows in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conſideration puts the Church upon thoſe Melancholy Infidell reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſad Expoſtulations. v. 7, 8, 9. but verſe 10. begins the Pſalme of Remembrance, where we have the Church correcting the weakneſſe of her former Expreſſions, and her ſelf for them; and betaking her ſelf for ſhelter to that ſure Refuge, the experience ſhe has formerly had of Gods goodneſſe and power, in her greateſt ſtraights; to the remembrance of the years of that Right-hand of the Moſt High, which can never be ſhortned. So that let the preſent yoak be never ſo heavy, yet the conſideration of that Right-hand which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109337:6"/> ſhooke off that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> may ſupport and eaſe you under it.</p>
            <p>This uſe the Spirit of God in Scripture frequently makes of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> deliverance, as in other places, ſo <hi>Pſalme</hi> 74. v. 14. <hi>Thou breakeſt the head of</hi> Leviathan <hi>in pieces, and gaveſt him to be meat for the People inhabiting the Wilderneſſe.</hi> His meaning doubtleſſe may be, that whereas the People in their ſtraights in the Wilderneſſe, might be tempted to doubt of or diſtruſt the Providence of God towards them: To prevent this, God had given them <hi>Leviathan</hi> as food for their Faith, which was ſufficient to uphold their ſpirits, and maintain a life of Hope and Confidence within them; if they would but look up unto him, and make their dependance upon him, according to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious incouragement, and triumphing provocation of ſo great and unheard of a Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Aſaph</hi> here takes the ſame courſe, with the diſtreſſed Church when in a wilderneſſe condition, hungry and thirſty, their ſouls faint wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hin them: He goes to <hi>Leviathan,</hi> whom God had broken in pieces, and ſets him before them for meat, (from the 14. verſe to the words of my Text.) And here leſt God ſhould be thought not to ſave to the utmoſt, but onely for his own Name-ſake to reſcue from ſome eminent danger, and ſo leave them to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; we are aſſured that after he had been their Deliverer, himſelf alſo became their Conductor, and whereas they were a Rude, Ungovern'd and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed multitude, he crowns them with the bleſſing of a Gracious Governour, and Regular Government, leading them with as much care, as the moſt vigilant Shepheard his flock, <hi>By the hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron.</p>
            <p>The words are plain, the ſenſe is clear and evident, and therefore it would be but loſt labour farther to expound them. What is requiſite this way ſhall be taken notice of as we paſſe, in the mean time, we have here theſe three things Obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Supreme Governor, together with the Divine Inſtitution of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Government, and that over his own peculiar People, in theſe words; <hi>Thou leadeſt thy People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We have here his Vicegerent <hi>Moſes,</hi> deriving immediately from him, and placed next even to God himſelf, with the Subordination of <hi>Aaron</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for 'tis <hi>By the Hand,</hi> not the Hands, more Fingers it ſeems, but one Hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is the manner of Gods Conduct, implyed in theſe words, <hi>As a flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall take them in their order, and in the firſt of them, theſe three things again offer themſelves to our Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:109337:6"/>1. The Divine Originall of Government, or its Author God, implyed in the word, <hi>Thou.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Bleſſing of a Lawfull Governour and Regular Government, couched under a paſtorall Metaphor, <hi>Leadeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The People bleſſed by being thus made ſubject; his own People, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> whom he had choſen.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God leads.</hi> God is the Author, or Power belongeth unto God, it derives from him and is ſtill managed by him, who is here ſaid to lead by the hands of them he intruſts with Scepters; the hand is the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> but the arm is an arm of Omnipotency, wrapt up in the Clouds, ſuch divine things will God have Kings to be reputed, that he challenges almoſt every thing about them for his own, the Oyle wherewith they are Anointed is Gods Oyle, their Thrones are Gods Thrones, the Judgement they execute is Gods Judgement, their Kingdome is Gods Kingdome. Hence they are called the Sons of God, yea Gods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a paſſage in <hi>Tully</hi> concerning the Tragicall Poets, to this purpoſe; <hi>Quando fabulae ſuae exitum reperire non poſſunt recurrunt ad Deum:</hi> What they did fabulouſly, we may; nay muſt, do truly; if we will find out the pedigree of Supremacy, for it is <hi>Coeli depoſitum,</hi> which like that Scepter in <hi>Homer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by innumerable Predeceſſors unto <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> was firſt handed down from <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo every other Princes face ſhines with the glorious beams of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power communicated unto them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od who by an Omnipotent <hi>fiat</hi> firſt called the paſſible world into Act, and hath ever ſince laid out the ſame power for preſerving what at firſt he created. That God (I ſay) by vertue of his Dominion over all, and for the good of the whole, firſt placed this part of his own Image in fathers of families, (for Dominion doubtleſſe was at firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.)</p>
            <p>But when a <hi>Nimrod</hi> aroſe, with hounds at his heels, and began to hunt men, neceſſity became a vertue, and what they could not do in their ſingle capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they endeavoured to effect by joynt engagement; the weakneſſe of each individuall, being back'd by the united ſtrength of the ſociety unto which he adhered.</p>
            <p>This the Ancients ſignifie by the Harp of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> which charm'd, that is, civilized men as ſavage as Lions and Tigres, whereby they were brought to ſubmit themſelves to Governours, and yield up part of their naturall, for the preſervation of their civil and religious rights; yea, of their very Beings. Without this our Streets would immediately be turned into Shambles, and our Houſes filled with Tragedies. Anarchy, but for a ſhort ſpace would beget more
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109337:7"/> confuſion, then when <hi>Phaeton</hi> drove the Chariot of the Sun out of its courſe, and put the whole world into a combuſtion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſians</hi> therefore had a Cuſtome, that when their Princes dyed, four or five days of miſrule were indulged the People, in which they might do what they liſted without controul, that by the Rapines and Outrages, which might well be thought would be committed therein, they might be brought the more in love with the perſon and government of their ſucceeding Prince.</p>
            <p>It is a ſad way, I confeſſe, but a ſure one, to know the happineſſe of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by experimenting the confuſion of Anarchy; witneſſe our own late diſmall and tragicall conſequences of no King in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore ever bleſſed be the name of that God, who for the good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and preſervation of Humane ſociety, hath intruſted Kings with a power over the Eſtates and lives of others, which truſt could be of no validity, if repoſed in them by any other ſave him alone, who by vertue of his Supreme Authority had a power over both; and ſo could diſpence with thoſe Laws other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in force both againſt Murder and Theft. Man hath not an abſolute power over his own life, and therefore cannot beſtow it upon an other, the Charter by which the Magiſtrate acts in ſuch caſes is ſealed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> Without this Divine Sanction from the Supreame Law-giver, the very Sword of Juſtice would have committed Murder, as often as it had been dipt in the blood of Malefactors.</p>
            <p>For what had the Magiſtrate to do to take away the life of his fellow crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were he not Gods Miniſter impowred and ordained by him to execute wrath on evil doers?</p>
            <p>It was a Miracle among the Heathen, that ſo many Nations, yea, Kings and Princes, ſhould give their Heads to One, ſometimes a Woman, ſometimes a Child; which argueth, that by the Light of Nature they ſaw ſuch impreſſions of Divinity ſtamped on them, as rendred their perſons more Sacred, Auguſt and Venerable, than what was meerly Humane.</p>
            <p>That power given to Kings and Princes over others, is a Divine Inſtitution, the conſent of moſt Authors both Ancient and Modern, Sacred and Prophane do abundantly confirme, who are frequently acted both by Caſuiſts and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall Divines treating on this ſubject. I ſhall mention onely two or three and ſo proceed.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath ſaid enough alone in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which may be tranſlated out of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 13. v. 1. <hi>The Powers that be, are ordained of God,</hi> to which alſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> beareth witneſſe. A Chriſtian (ſaith he) is no Mans enemy, much leſſe the Emperours, whom he knows to be appointed by his God. <hi>Colamus ergo Imperatorem.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Go therefore reverence the Emperour as a Man next to God, and as one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109337:7"/> that hath obtained, what ever he hath gotten from God. And elſewhere, whence comes the Emperour? whence comes his Power? whence comes his Spirit? which he learned from <hi>Irenaeus</hi> before him. He whoſe powerfull word creates ſouls, the ſame creates Princes and Potentates.</p>
            <p>But we need not go to <hi>Ophir</hi> for gold, the Scripture is a rich Mine, out of which we may digg abundantly to overlay this part of Gods Arke, both within and without, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 62.11. <hi>God hath ſpoken it again and again, that power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to himſelf.</hi> Pſalm. 47.9. <hi>The Shields of the earth they are the Lords,</hi> they bear his Arms and Inſcription, he holds them up and over the world. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 22.28. <hi>The Kingdome is the Lords, and he is the Governour among the Nations.</hi> No power is of force, but what is from above; as the whole ſcope and drift of the 13. to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſufficiently demonſtrates, from which is there rightly infer'd an injunction to Obedience under penalty of Damnation verſe 2.</p>
            <p>This Truth is that ſtone in <hi>Jeremie,</hi> which not only ſupports <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezars,</hi> but the Thrones of all the Kings upon earth. Truly Brethren, thoſe Melodious Aires of rareſt Muſick, thoſe Triumphant Arches, Magnificent Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, that Train of Nobles, Knights, and Gentry, the Crown of pure Gold, together with a glorious Throne and Scepter, are all requiſite and ſuitable to the ſtate of King and Kingdome, and apt to beget Awe and Reverence in the hearts of the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>But alas, this is but the outſide and ceremony of the Sacred Majeſty of God, whoſe repreſentative the King is, whoſe judgment he pronounceth; This, this is that which renders him truly Sacred to all religious and judicious men and minds. Divinity is the maintainer of Civil honour, and Religion bears up the Throne in due reverence, whilſt Men are taught to diſcern God as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the chief hand and ſtroke in government, by whom Kings raign and Princes decree juſtice whilſt they are taught (I ſay) to ſee God leading: <hi>by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Away then with that Irreligious and Dangerous Tenet, ſo frequent in the Mouths and Pens of ſome Men in theſe days, that all power is from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, interpreting I know not by what Authority, <hi>Dei Miniſter,</hi> the Peoples Servant. That Magiſtrates, yea, even the Supreme Magiſtrate is truſted by the People, and if he be not faithfull, that is, if he ſatisfie not their giddy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, (which in Prudence and Conſcience he is bound not to do,) then they may aſſert their native rights, and reaſſume the truſt repoſed in them. Thus doth this pernicious Errour pretend to a Law of Nature for the violation of all the Laws both of God and Man. A Doctrine big with Rebellion and Confuſion, whoſe teeming Wombe, never brings forth any other Iſſue but Blood, and Fire, and Pillars of Smoak.</p>
            <p>I hope I have demonſtrated unto you, that power derives from a higher
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109337:8"/> houſe, and that the Magiſtrates Charter is not ſo drawn, as to be revoked again at the Peoples pleaſure; that the Supreme Magiſtrate is Gods Deputy, and ſo accountable to no creature whatſoever, becauſe ſubject to no Man or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Men whatever.</p>
            <p>This the Heathen Sages knew well, and therefore that their Laws might be the more inviolably obſerved, pretended ſtill they were enacted by the aſſiſtance of a Divine Wiſdome. Thus <hi>Lycurgus</hi> impoſeth upon <hi>Spartae,</hi> by the help of the Oracle at <hi>Delphos. Numa</hi> on the <hi>Romans,</hi> by a ſuppoſed privated commerce with the Goddeſs <hi>Egeria;</hi> the like may be ſaid of <hi>Solon</hi> and the reſt. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homets</hi> Impoſtures had never been ſo taking but that he perſwaded his deluded Followers, that they were whiſper'd into his Ear, by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>From all which we may infer, that then both Laws and Law-givers have their due honour from the People, when they can look through the cloud and ſmoak, and hear God dictating the one, and ſee him acting in the other.</p>
            <p>And this may ſuffice touching the Divine Originall of Government, imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the word <hi>Thou;</hi> the benefits follow, couched under a Paſtorall Metaphor, <hi>Leadeſt.</hi> This implies a motion whereby ſomething more inconvenient is avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſomething more convenient obtained; and as all other motions, ſo this hath its two Terms. <hi>A quo,</hi> and <hi>ad Quem:</hi> The Term from which is <hi>Egypt,</hi> a Land of Slavery and Idolatry; the Term to which is <hi>Canaan,</hi> a Land wherein he will ſet them at liberty, and eſtabliſh true piety. But let us take a ſhort view of the Bondage, that ſo we may learn to ſet the higher value on the Deliverance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This bondage lay moſt heavy on their Eſtates, ſo that though at firſt they were ſeated in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> yet now made uſe of but as ſponges, which the Tyrant and his Task-maſters ſqueezed at their pleaſures; here to have been a good Husband, was the readieſt way to have been a bad Subject, and then expoſed as a prey to the Talons of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s State Vultures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But food and raiment was all <hi>Jacob</hi> would bartar with Heaven for, that God might be his God, and he his Servant; and therefore as long as they breath free Aire, go and come at their pleaſure, no matter for ſo many full Baggs or cramb'd Coffers, their Souls motion towards Heaven was like to be ſo much the ſwifter, for that their Bodies were not loaden and clog'd with thick Clay. But here's their miſery, to the burden of Poverty was added alſo the loſſe of their Liberty, for you could hardly find one of the race of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who had the ſpirit of a true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> in him, but either in the Brick-kilns and Mortar, or elſe the Stocks hurting his Feet, and the Iron entring into his Soul.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But Eſtate and Freedome, yea all is well ſold, ſo we may have but Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erty of Conſcience for it: This indeed coſt them very dear, but then ſee what it amounted too, truly no more but a wild permiſſion tolerating any other, ſave
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109337:8"/> the true worſhip of the true God. They might perhaps worſhip <hi>Iſis, Anubis</hi> or <hi>Serapis,</hi> either Crocodiles or Serpent, Onions or Garlike, which the Poet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>outs with a
<q>
                  <l>Felices nemium, quibus haec naſcuntur in Hortis.</l>
                  <l>Numina,— </l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>[Juvena.]</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, other things, as the Red-cloth. <hi>Varro</hi> reckons up among many hundreds of other <hi>Pagan</hi> Deities, whilſt ſacrificing to the true God only was an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> Saints, whoſe Religions were full as various as their Faces, and ſo much was worſhip'd that there was nothing left to be worſhip'd.</p>
            <p>Now if the Impure Converſation of the <hi>Sodomites</hi> were ſuch a corroſive to juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> if <hi>Davids</hi> eyes ran down with water becauſe men kept not Gods Commandements, much more muſt it grieve the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſee the Glory of the God of their Fathers given to ſuch baſe Creatures.</p>
            <p>But that which yet makes their miſery exceeding miſerable, was that they never petitioned for redreſs, but their return was an hard an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer, and freſh impoſition: <hi>Ye are Idle, ye are Idle,</hi> let therefore the allowance of Straw be withdrawn, and the tale of Brick be doubled; and thus they made them ſerve with rigour, rendring their lives bitter unto them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Egypt</hi> is eaſily tranſlated into <hi>England,</hi> and then farther Application will be needleſs; we had our <hi>Egypt,</hi> our <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and our Task-maſters too, nor were Gods appearances leſs glorious in breaking our <hi>Egyptian</hi> yoke. He hath raiſed up <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and now leads us by them; here is the difference, God was forty years leading them to their <hi>Canaan,</hi> but hath within the ſpace of twenty Months brought us to much more then we could hope, and indeed all we can deſire; they had their Wilderneſs and Red-ſea to paſſe through, but God found out a nearer way for us, abating both.</p>
            <p>You have now ſeen from whence it is that God leads, let us now with him take a view from <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and ſee whither it is he leads them. And that is from <hi>Egypt to Canaan,</hi> from Onions and Garlick, to Milk and Honey; from Slavery and Idolatry to true Liberty and Piety; from Temporall and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Preſſures, to Temporall and Spirituall Happineſs.</p>
            <p>For their Eſtates, the Judiciall Law ſtood as a Wall of Fire round about them, ſecuring their Proſperity, and encouraging their Induſtry, ſince they might be ſure to enjoy what they had whilſt they lived, and after leave the reſt of their ſubſtance to their Babes; they were now under known Laws, not arbitrary Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſame Law alſo which ſecured their Propriety; was alſo the fence of their Liberty; they were as free as the Aire they breathed in, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſubjection to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> for this is the true nature of Liberty,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109337:9"/> to enjoy the benefit of good Laws and juſt Governors, and not to bear a ſhare in the government it ſelf, to reap the fruits of Diſtributive and Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juſtice, the Pillars of State from the hands of ſuch as God hath inſtruſted with the Sword.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the ſatisfying and quieting of their Conſciences, all was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Pattern in the Mount. Ah bleſſed change! from the Temples of <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Anubis,</hi> to the Tabernacle in <hi>Salem,</hi> and the Name made ſo great in <hi>Sion;</hi> yea as the happineſs of man is that of Time which is preſent, or that of Eternity which is to commence when Time ſhall be no more; ſo <hi>Canaan</hi> is put for both being the Type of Temporall and Eternall Happineſs, of an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradiſe and of an Heavenly, called the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which is above, and is free, the Mother of us all. Now from this ſlavery both of Body and Soul to this Land of Liberty and true Piety, from danger as to our preſent and future eſtates, to a ſecurity both of Temporall and Eternall Happineſs. God leads his people <hi>by the Hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and of</hi> Aaron.</p>
            <p>And thus by opening the Terms, I have alſo intimated the Benefits of a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Governour and Regular Government, couched under the Metaphor, <hi>Leadeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Now follows the third thing propoſed in the firſt Generall, the Perſons who were thus made Happy, in theſe words, <hi>His People,</hi> Gods People you ſee they are, he owns them ſtill, though in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>Red-ſea,</hi> or <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> He ceaſeth not to Love them, becauſe the World Hateth them: when he makes up his Jewells be will be mindfull of them as precious things, though repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the off-ſcouring of all things. Outward properity is ſo far from being a mark of the true Church, that the contrary is moſt true, the Perſecutors thereof being oftentimes ſucceſsfull and lucky Villains; yet he who ſets bounds to the Sea, hath ſaid to the proud Waves of their rage and malice alſo, <hi>hither ſhall ye come and no further:</hi> yea, ſo gloriouſly doth he appear for their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, as if he intended nothing more then to convince his and his Churches Enemies, that he is with his Buſh in the Hotteſt Flames, and with his Lillies amongſt the Sharpeſt Thornes, that ſo all things may work together for the good of his Church and People.</p>
            <p>This Note I ſhall not inſiſt upon, though I could not but glance at it as I paſſed; that which is more obſervable is, that though they were Gods pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar People, yet they are under <hi>Moſes</hi>'s conduct, this can be no plea to exempt them from their Allegiance, and Duty to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſince it is the beſt evidence of being his People, when we reverence his Image in thoſe he hath ſet over us. If any People in the world, theſe here in the Text might have ſhaken of the Yoak of Obedience and Loyalty upon this pretence, for they were his People more then any Nation under Heaven ſeverall ways.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109337:9"/>1. They were his People by Covenant; I mean not ſuch a Covenant as <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> and his Brethren in that conſpiracy entred into, a Covenant conceiv'd in Treaſon and brought forth in Blood and Rebellion, wherein they plighted their faith each to other by quaffing of whole Goblets of humane Blood; nor ſuch a one as <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> tells us, was falſly laid to the charge of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, no Holy League of <hi>France;</hi> but I mean that Covenant ſealed in Heaven by the blood of the Lamb ſlain from Eternity, publiſhed in the infancy of the world in theſe words, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head,</hi> and afterwards renewed with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. and ſealed with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Circumciſion, wherein God covenants, that he will be their God, and that they ſhall be his People.</p>
            <p>Almoſt every Scripture where the word <hi>Covenant</hi> is but named, hath been groſly abuſed in theſe laſt and worſt times, whilſt that which concerns the great Covenant made by God in Chriſt with loſt man, or if you will, thoſe Eternall tranſactions betwixt God and Chriſt for the Redemption of the World, are frequently applyed to their own, that I ſay no worſe, illegall and unwarrantable conſpiracies and combinations, whereas Gods Covenant is very conſiſtent with <hi>Moſes</hi> Conduct, by Gods Covenant his Peope are more engaged to be obedient.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They were his People by that ſpeciall care he took for them, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence by which he watched over them, four hundred years together, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> came into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſojourned in the Land of <hi>Ham, Pſal.</hi> 105.23. when he ſent one before to provide them bread, and pay his Brethren for ſelling him: when he preſerved and encreaſed his flock, though in the midſt of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as Sheep among Wolves, or Lambs in the midſt of Lions; and when his time of deliverance was come, he carried them out with a mighty Hand, and out-ſtretched Arme, ſhewing Signes among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and Wonders in their Land, yet we never find that they urged Providence to ruin <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They were his People by ſpeciall Conduct, he went before them in a Pillar of a Cloud by day, and a Pillar of Fire by Night; yea, his Angels were made Miniſtring Spirits for their good, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20, 23. and yet we find not that when <hi>Moſes</hi> executes Gods Laws, they cry out, we will have King <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> or King <hi>Serakhim,</hi> or King <hi>Jeſus,</hi> we will not have this <hi>Moſes</hi> to raign over us; for they knew that being in Covenant with King <hi>Jehovah,</hi> they were the more engaged to be obedient unto <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of the Lord, their lawfull Governour: Yea, if any of them began to Murmur, that their Governours took too much upon them, ſince all the Congregation were the <hi>Lords People,</hi> or <hi>Holy</hi> as well as they; ſo far is ſuch a pretence from bearing them out, that it ſeems to haſten, yea, and heighen their judgment too; for God will not ſuffer them to dye an ordinary death, but opens the earth, and as it were by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109337:10"/> a Trap-door lets them down a nearer way into the bottomeleſs pit, as in the caſe of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Competitors.</p>
            <p>There were in thoſe days neither <hi>Phariſees, Saduces</hi> nor <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> 'twas in after-ages that the Corruption of the Church prov'd the Generation of theſe Sects, and therefore by Gods People here is meant a National not a Congregational Church over the whole twelve Tribes, not ſome few choice ones of our own Tribe, whom we ſtile the Elect, and therefore ſeperate them as the precious from the vile, as if by a more diſcerning eye then that of ordinary Mortals, we had pierced the Clouds, and read over the Iron Leaves of Eternity, and could now perfectly tell whoſe names were written moſt fairly in the Book of Life.</p>
            <p>Not a people of God, I ſay, pick'd and cull'd out of the People of God, as if we meant to pair the Onion till nothing remained, rending not only Chriſts ſeamleſs Coat, but his very Body into pieces, and crumbling it into at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes. The Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> not ſome certain Sects &amp; Factions, are here ſtyled Gods People, and not only here, but throughout the Old Teſtament, <hi>The ſeed of Abraham:</hi> The people of the <hi>Jews</hi> in contradiſtinction to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Nations round about, were by a ſpeciall Title called Gods People; as in the New Teſtament thoſe that were converted from Gentiliſme or Judaiſme to the Goſpel of Chriſt, were called Saints, and the Church, (for the Church at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> is the ſame with the Saints at <hi>Corinth,</hi>) and both with the Chriſtians or Profeſſors of Chriſtianity at <hi>Corinth,</hi> in the New-Teſtament Language, which I have the rather a little inſiſted on, becauſe no one expreſſion was ever abuſed to viler ends and purpoſes, then this of Gods People and Saints. Gods People, they are the Apple of his Eye, and Saints ought to be precious in Ours; but when we will upon preſumption of our own Saintſhip, reproach others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the ſame Goſpel with our ſelves, having the ſame grace for their way, and glory in their eye; when, I ſay, upon ſuch a preſumption we brand our Chriſtian-Brethren for Hypocrites, that we forſooth are <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſo make no Conſcience to rob and ſpoil them; pretending in our Profeſſion to a higher pitch of Piety, but in our Practiſe falling down below the Rules of Common Honeſty.</p>
            <p>All that I ſhall ſay more to this ſort of men is, that thoſe Pictures which with one light give you the reſemblance of a Saint, and with another of a Friend, may well ſet forth to the life, and be the Emblemes of ſuch Saints, who under this Vizzard act ſuch things, as Hell it ſelf ſtands amaz'd to ſee, and ſo become a ſhame to thoſe who are Saints indeed, and a ſcandall to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf; and yet, all this in order to the advancement of the Saints intereſt, and by ſuch who have appropriated the name of Gods People and Heires of Promiſe to themſelves, and would fain inherit under that Title; Becauſe they have learnt to Cant in Scripture phraſe, and abuſe the Language of the Holy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109337:10"/> Ghoſt, converting it into meer gibberidge, and bending the higheſt things to ſerve the loweſt and baſeſt ends.</p>
            <p>But the people with whom we have to do were <hi>Iſrael</hi> indeed, Gods own people, even the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom he had preſerved and delivered; and now that he might make up their mercies complete, leads them by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond General, where we have <hi>Moſes</hi> Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, deriving immediately from him, and placed next to God himſelf, with the ſubordination of <hi>Aaron</hi> implied, for 'tis <hi>by the hand,</hi> not hands, more fingers it ſeems, but one hand. Three things here alſo implied.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> the Supreme next to God. 2. <hi>Aaron</hi> in Subordination, or next to <hi>Moſes.</hi> 3. Both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> make up but one hand, they have, it ſeems, no more in this great work of conducting Gods people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here we ſhall conſider <hi>Moſes,</hi> 1. in his Perſonal capacity; 2. in his Political; and ſhew you in every reſpect, God hath owned him as a perſon moſt fit to be the Leader of his People. But I would not be miſtaken, as if I intended to give <hi>Korah</hi> and his company occaſion, or ground of framing a diſtinction betwixt the Abſtract and Concrete, that ſo they may oppoſe and reſiſt the Perſon in power, whilſt they pretend to own and reverence the Power of the perſon; a Doctrine, than which, nothing can be more deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive both to Governors and Government. But to ſhew what a ſpecial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence watches over their perſons, whom he will advance to the honour of leading his people; and therefore how ſacred they ought to be to us, ſince they are ſo dear to him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes,</hi> as his name imports, was drawn out of the floods, out of the waters of many troubles doth God reſcue him, that he might lead his people by thoſe ſtill waters of Comfort and Order, which run moſt pleaſantly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God uſeth a weak Inſtrument, that his own glory may be the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous; he makes uſe of a woman to preſerve, conceal, and protect his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> a woman, I ſay, whoſe memory is recorded in holy Writ, and ſhall flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, yea does, now that the memory of thoſe Inſtruments of cruelty, thoſe ſons of violence, is periſhed with them; and the Tyrant is remembred, yet 'tis ſo, as that he were better be forgotten: I had rather, ſays he, no body ſhould ever know there was ſuch a man as <hi>Plutarch,</hi> than be remembred onely for devouring Infants, and furniſhing the world with Tragedies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He turns all to the advantage of the Church and People, by giving here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their <hi>Moſes</hi> Princely education in the Court of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came learned in all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> wiſe as an Angel of God, and ſo mighty both in word and deed. Thus the Lion's Den became a ſhelter to the Lamb, even the meekeſt upon earth in whatſoever concerned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109337:11"/> but moſt zealous for the glory of God, and good of his Church.</p>
            <p>Now by ſuch a <hi>Moſes,</hi> thus preſerved in the day of hazard and peril, thus protected and educated, will God lead his people as a flock from <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſlavery to liberty, from miſery not to be expreſſed, to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs beyond what we could conceive; for as this deliverance 'twas true too, <hi>When God turned our captiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, then were we like them that dream.</hi> But that which completes this mercy, giving it all its dimenſions, is, that Gods hand hath appeared all along in it, that the very enemies to truth and peace muſt confeſs, It is the Lords doing, and wonderful in the eyes of all the world; it came not like one of thoſe common mercies, which God ſeems to hurle about the world, and ſcatter (as it were) at all adventures; 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Ex Deliberatione, &amp;</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Ex Dilectione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From the depth of Counſel and Wiſdom, God ſeems after a deep delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (abating ſtill the imperfections which accompany ſuch acts in us) to pitch upon our King as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> upon <hi>Joſeph, Gen.</hi> 41.38. <hi>Can we find ſuch a man again as this?</hi> or as himſelf did of old upon <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. <hi>The Lord ſought him a man after his own heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Samuel,</hi> there alluding to the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny among the ſons of <hi>Jeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This mercy proceeded, as from the depth of Counſel, ſo from the heighth of Love and Affection, from thoſe turnings of his bowels which were ever to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. Should we now expoſtulate with God, and ſay, <hi>Wherein haſt thou loved us?</hi> why, there is a ſufficient evidence of his love, in that he hath given us a King, yea, ſuch a King: The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> took notice of this as the greateſt manifeſtation of his love to his people of old; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in thee, to ſet thee on the throne of Iſrael; becauſe the Lord loved Iſrael for ever, therefore made he thee King to do judgment and j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtice,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.9. Should not we now thankfully ack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owledge and highly value this fruit of Gods love, the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> would riſe up in judgment againſt us, and condemn us.</p>
            <p>I have now done with his Perſonal Capacity, and ſhall now treat of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical, under theſe two Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtands next to God.</item>
               <item>2. He ſtands alone there, without any Compeers or Co-ordinates.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. God alone is over <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he immediately und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r God, and all the people under him; ſo that <hi>Moſes</hi> may ſay with the Centurion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9. <hi>I am under authority,</hi> he was under <hi>Claudius Lyſias,</hi> and he under <hi>Felix,</hi> and he under the Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eror, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c pro Deus</hi> under God, and ſo under Authority alſo; but ſo much above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll other humane Authority, that the people are ſaid to ask counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of God wh n they conſulted <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 18.1.</p>
            <p>It is eſſential to the order of Governing, that a Supremacy of power be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109337:11"/> ſomewhere by God, queſtionable onely by himſelf.</p>
            <q>Reges in Ipſos Imperium eſt Jovis.</q>
            <p>Neither is this truly ſaid onely of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e beſt and nobleſt, but alſo of <hi>Democracy,</hi> the worſt and baſeſt of Governments; 'tis as very a Monſter as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which have faces of men in their breaſts, but are without a Head; yet even here the people will have ſome to govern the reſt, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves, againſt whom there ſhall be no riſing up.</p>
            <p>That you may never again be miſtaken in this point, becauſe a miſtake will be of very dangerous conſequence, I ſhall ſpend a little time, and take a little pains in opening the nature of this Supremacy, and acquainting you with the latitude and extent of it. And here for your better information I ſhall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to explain, firſt, the <hi>Quid nominis,</hi> or thoſe words and ſingle terms in which the Scripture expreſſeth it: Secondly, the <hi>Quid rei,</hi> what be the Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients or conſtituent parts of this Supremacy?</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt of theſe we find three words in Scripture, the firſt ſhall be that of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where ſuch ſeem to be diſtinguiſhed from Kings, and ſo muſt ſignifie either thoſe, who under other forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment managed the Supreme power, and yet were not Kings; or elſe thoſe in places of eminency under Kings. Take it in which ſenſe you pleaſe, it infers the duties of the firſt verſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Supplications, Prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for</hi> them. Still, I ſay, it ſecures Supremacy, rendring it ſacred and inviolable.</p>
            <p>Nor would I be miſunderſtood, as if I thought there were any thing in this Scripture for the ſupport and bolſtring up of Oppreſſion and Uſurpation; an Uſurper alters the caſe, and there is no juſt ſcruple but thoſe may be turned out by force according to Law, who come in by force againſt Law, as in the ſtory of <hi>Athaliah</hi> deſtroyed by <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> whereby <hi>Joaſh,</hi> who had true title, was eſtabliſhed in the Throne: All that can be ſaid, is, that it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures their perſons who are entruſted with the Supreme Power, either in Ariſtocratical or Democratical Dukedoms or States; all that are thus juſtly in the poſſeſſion of Supremacy, have a Title to Prayers and Thankſgivings.</p>
            <p>An eminently learned<note n="*" place="margin">B. <hi>Andrews</hi> on the Commandements.</note> Prelate of our own interpoſeth this word, <hi>An Excellency of a Gift;</hi> when a man ha h ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what above others, either by Birth, or Natural, or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Endowm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, as well as Places.</p>
            <p>By Birth, Nobility doubtleſſe gives great capacity of Rule and Authority, 'tis the Quarry out of which God raiſeth the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces of his people. 'Twas a character of the worſt of times, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.5. when <hi>the child behaved himſelf
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109337:12"/> proudly againſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the honorable. Tobias</hi> the ſervant is not fit to rule, nor <hi>Abimelech</hi> the ſon of an handmaid, nor muſt <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi>'s Bramble be preferred and promoted over the Trees.</p>
            <p>Now, if this be the ſenſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am ſure it ſecures our Soveraigns Title to all the duties of the firſt verſe, end engageth us to be more devout in them this day, yea, every day. Our Land is bleſſed in having <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſon of Nobles for its King, one who ſways Scepters tranſmitted to him from enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Kings and Princes his Predeceſſors; and therefore is in this ſenſe amongſt thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and hath the excellency of this gift.</p>
            <p>For the other gifts of Natural or Acquired Qualifications and Endowments, though I am far from their opinion who hold, that Dominion is founded in grace; far, I ſay, from caſting an Utopian Prince in <hi>Zenophon</hi>'s mold, as being well aſſured that <hi>Zerubbabel</hi>'s Title is his being the ſon of <hi>Shealtiel, Hag.</hi> 2.23. yet I think I may ſafely ſay, and that without the leaſt ſuſpition of flattery, that if we were to chuſe a King for ſuch natural and acquired endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as might capacitate him for ſo high an employment, we could never make a better choice than God has made for us, which is ſo clear a truth, that I hope you all bear witneſs to it, and rejoyce in it this day. We are called to rejoyce in, and to bleſs God for the beſt of men, as well as of Kings, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it may ſignifie the excellency of thoſe gifts alſo, entitles our Soveraign to, and engages us to be the more devout in, the duties of the firſt verſe, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this day, but I ſay again, every day. You will, I hope, pardon the digreſſion I have made in explicating the firſt word, ſince it has been no very impertinent one, and I ſhall be the briefer in the other two: the next of which is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. a Power, or a Sword, without which, ſays the ſame learned and reverend Prelate, all is a ſhadow. They are not here to be heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to, who interpret <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a lawful power, that is according to them, a power commanding lawful things, as if as ſoon as the Prince commands un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful things, or ſuch as we think ſo, the reins are then thrown upon our necks, and we are let looſe into an active reſiſtance of ſuch commands: This uſe has been made of this Expoſition, but I hope for ever to ſuppreſs and ſilence it, when I come unto the third word; in the interim, take the word in either ſenſe, either for a Power lawfully deriv'd and acquir'd, or lawfully us'd, it ſecures our Soveraign, and ſubjects thoſe who will not be his obedient and loyal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the damnation of the ſecond verſe.</p>
            <p>The third word by which the Scripture expreſſes Supremacy or Soveraignty, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> Principality, or a place of Government to exerciſe his gift and power in. And if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this ſenſe gives a title to Soveraignty, King <hi>CHARLS</hi> has as large a one as three Kingdoms can give him. But for ſilencing that Expoſition of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even now mentioned, know, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109337:12"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are uſed promiſcuouſly, and <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. are joyned together, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are charged to mind men of being ſubject unto both, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; So that though there be not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ſenſe ſome contend for, yet if there be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you muſt practice, and we muſt both preach and practiſe ſubjection and obedience unto it. Now place Supremacy in one, or in all theſe, for they have an affinity, and it imports a power over all thoſe, that God has ſubjected unto them, uncontroulable by any, ſave God himſelf, and is thus defined by the learned<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de qui Belli &amp; Pac. c. <hi>3.</hi> § <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Grotius, Illa dicitur ſumma po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas cuju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> actus alterius juri non ſubſunt, ita ut alterius vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis humanae arbitrio irriti poſſint reddi;</hi> That Power is tearmed Supreme whoſe acts are not ſubject to anothers Law, ſo that they may be rendred null and void at the pleaſure of any others will whatſoever.</p>
            <p>The Ingredients, or Conſtitutive, and Integral parts of this Supremacy, as they are ſummed up by that excellent Author out of the fourth book of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Politicks, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. as alſo divers places of <hi>Dionyſius Halica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naſſenſis,</hi> may be reduced to theſe following heads:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jus legum condendarum &amp; tollendarum,</hi> a power of making and abrogating Laws, in which it is moſt certain our King is Supreme, however ſome men are otherwiſe prepoſſeſt, by Arguments drawn from three Eſtates, Coordinate <hi>quoad hoc,</hi> which were not indeed to be anſwered, were there any ſuch thing as ſuch a Co-ordination as they contend for. A King may be Supreme, and yet not abſolute, and that's our Soveraigns caſe; He is Supreme in making Laws, though not abſolute and alone; our Worthies in Parliament do not give their Soveraign Law, but they do <hi>legem petere &amp; rogare,</hi> 'tis the Royal Aſſent that ſpeaks a Bill into a Law. Which Supremacy reaches not onely to Civil, but Eccleſiaſtical Laws alſo, which in matters indifferent, and not againſt the clear evidence of Gods Word, are binding unto conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Jus decernendi de bello &amp; pace,</hi> a power to denounce War and conclude Peace, this power Gods Vice-gerent is entruſted with by God himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.9. there he is entruſted with the Sword and the Shield. And we read of the times when Kings go out to war.<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. contr. Fauſt in Manic. <hi>lib. 22. cap. 75.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ordo ille naturalis mortalium paci accommodus hoc poſſit, ut ſuſcipiendi belli authoritas at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> concilium penes principem ſit.</hi> Even natural order accommodate to the peace of mankind requiring this, that the power of making War remain wholly in the Prince; which when the people uſurped, we ſee they were puniſhed, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.43, 44. That the power of concluding Peace, and making Confederations and Leagues is alſo Soveraign, the examples of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> clearly evince, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.19. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.2. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 5.12. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.56.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109337:13"/>3. <hi>Jus Magiſtratuum creandorum, &amp;c.</hi> A power freely to elect their own Servants, and diſpoſe of all Offices in Church and State. This alſo is a Jewel of the Crown, and one of the Ingredients of Soveraignty. For Church-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſee the example of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.8, 9. for State-Aſſemblies, the example of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.4.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Judicia,</hi> to pardon offenders, or puniſh with death, as in <hi>Joab</hi>'s and <hi>Shimei</hi>'s caſes, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. yea, to receive Appeals from other Judicatures, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.10, 11. All this, and more alſo, does this learned man conclude muſt go to the conſtituting and making up the Supremacy, which God entruſts him withal whom he ſets over his people, next and immediately under himſelf.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Paladium,</hi> which whilſt preſerv'd inviolable, ſtands as a firm Fence round about a Nation or People, to preſerve and protect them in their rights and priviledges, both Civil and Religious; for by this truſt repoſed in the Prince it comes to paſs, that each ſingle perſon is fortified with the ſtrength of a Nation.</p>
            <p>I hope now it partly appears what Supremacy is, and with whom entruſted. Since then <hi>Moſes</hi> is this Supreme, placed by God next to himſelf, it neceſſarily follows, that nothing leſs than God can exact an account of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s carriage or miſcarriage; which is true of our <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo. 'Tis ſaid, that if the Sun will not run its race, or go its courſe, there be certain <hi>Eumenides</hi> who are to ſcourge him; if Kings and Princes will not do their duties, they ſhall hereafter find their <hi>Eumenides;</hi> but ſtill <hi>divino judicio ſunt reſervendi,</hi> they muſt be reſerv'd for Gods Tribunal: we may not wreſt the Iron Rod out of Gods hands, that with it we may daſh his Anointed in pieces as a Potters veſſel. Know this, that we ceaſe to be ſubjects when we fall to queſtioning Princes, and immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the danger of the Apoſtles condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch temptations ſhall at any time hereafter be laid before you, by which the weak and ignoranter ſort of people are apt to be deluded, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theſe Principles, let not the Oath of God be forgotten, nor how much it concerns you <hi>reddere juramentum Domino,</hi> to perform your Oath unto the Lord. Let never any hand be lifted up againſt our Soveraign, which has been laid upon the holy Goſpel in witneſs of our ſubmiſſion to him, as to him whom God has conſtituted Supreme in matters, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil. Nor may ſuch Orthodox Divinity be branded (as ſometimes it is) for Court-flattery, ſince we find by experience what great reaſon there is, that a generation amongſt us, animated with a ſpirit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, ſhould be inſtructed in ſuch Principles as theſe, at certain ſeaſons in our moſt publick Aſſemblies; 'twill be too late to think of reclaiming men with a Sermon of Allegiance, when the Trumpet ſounds to the tune of that in
<pb facs="tcp:109337:13"/> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.16. <hi>What portion have we in David? we have no inheritance in the ſon of Jeſſe: to your tents, O Iſrael: now look to thine houſe, David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt, wherein I have acquainted you with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and place, and upon that the peoples duty, all which will yet appear much more evidently, when as I have ſhewed that he ſtands next to God, ſo I ſhall have proved that he ſtands alone there. For though <hi>Aaron</hi> ſeems to be joyned with him, yet we doubt not but as we paſs, to ſet him in his due ſubordination: now where there is a due ſubordination, the <hi>Dominus &amp; Servus,</hi> make up but <hi>unem aegens,</hi> Maſter and Servant are but one agent, and ſo 'tis but <hi>the hand,</hi> though impowred and actuated both by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I AM</hi> ſent <hi>Moſes,</hi> and if God commiſſion'd him, we cannot well imagine he ſhould ſet up any other government over his People here on Earth, then that which he himſelf exerciſeth over his Saints and Angels in Heaven; no more Kings there then Gods, Unity is convertible with Entity, and therefore chiefly with the Being of Beings. God is King in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and Chriſt is King in <hi>Sion,</hi> in this office he accompliſhed the great work of the worlds redemption,<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Copleſton Bampfields</hi> Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this year.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the Motto which Loyalty has this year written upon publick Banners, and it is no more then I believe, experience hath long ago engraven upon all our hearts. Two Suns would ſet the World into a combuſtion, more winds cauſe a Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane, and gather up nothing but Straw and Stubble, and light matter together; <hi>Regni ſocietas neque unquam cum fide incepit, neque ſine ſanguine deſiit,</hi> ſays the eloquent <hi>Minuc. Felix.</hi> Partnerſhip in ſupremacy always began treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and ended bloodily. The Scepter in the hand of one, is doubtleſs more ſteddy and upright, then of many; and as we find one ſoul to govern one body, and when it ceaſes to be one, the body is diſſolved; ſo we may obſerve that the greateſt Empir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that ever were, grew great by Monarchy, which ſoon crumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away when ſhared among the many. To ſpeak of the Originall of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, together with the advantages and bleſſings accompliſhing that, above any other Government whatſoever, is not my intent; nor is it requiſite, nor will the time permit; the worſt that can be ſaid is, that it may degenerate into Tyranny, but experience hath ſufficiently convinced us, that the teeth of many Harrows are far worſe then the point of one Sword. Monarchy is doubtleſs the way God intended the World ſhould be governed, that as he was moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent himſelf, and had all things under him, ſo there might be in his creatures alſo a pattern of that excellency and ſubjection; wherefore to honour Kings, when any excellent thing is to be ſet forth, the Scripture ſtyles it Kingly or like a King: Yea, ſo far, as one obſerves, did Chriſt honour <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as that he puts him before God, ſaying, give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> firſt, and then next give unto God, &amp;c. For he well knew the things of God would go on much the better, if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109337:14"/> thoſe of the King were well ordered; and it may be taken notice of, that he never Coin'd Money but once, and that miraculouſly in the mouth of a Fiſh, that <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> might not go without his due.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> you ſee ſtands next to God; he is ſupreme, yet not abſolute, <hi>id eſt,</hi> his will was not his law, for he was to act, <hi>ex praeſcripto,</hi> according to his pattern. And this may be the caſe of other Kings and Princes alſo, they may have a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme yet not an abſolute power, ſo that by reaſon either of Gods Laws, or a reſtraint from their own grants and poſitive conſtitutions, active obedience may not be due to their illegall commands, yet by reaſon of their ſupremacy, paſſive obedience becomes neceſſary under the penalty of damnation. We have heard, &amp; read much in theſe latter and worſer days, touching a mixt Monarchy, which yet has been ſufficiently demonſtrated to be but Anarchy; by it they mean a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy compounded of three Co-ordinate ſtates, which in plain Engliſh ſpeaks this Non-ſenſe, the power which one onely hath, is in three ſtates joyntly and equally.</p>
            <p>If reſtrained here to <hi>Moſes,</hi> then it follows <hi>Moſes</hi> was next to God alone, and yet the Princes, and Captains, and Prieſts aſſembled by the Silver Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, were next to God alſo, Co-ordinate with him in the ſupremacy, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate in any reſpect. If extended to us alſo, then not the King, but King, Lords, and Commons, are the joyntly the Supreme, and then the Correlate is wanting, none are left over whom they ſhould raign, we ſhould have a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without a Subject, becauſe all may challenge a ſhare in Soveraignty. And, becauſe I have heard many, whoſe Birth, Parts and Education, ſet them far above the Vulgar, urge arguments drawn from this falſe Topick of three Co-ordinate Eſtates, to confirm ſuch principles and practiſes, as I, and all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> or elſewhere, muſt and ought reſolutely to bear witneſs againſt; I ſhall for the ſatisfaction of them and others carried away with the ſame errour, here tranſcribe <hi>verbatim</hi> ſome paſſages out of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs,</hi> becauſe perhaps many may read that here which they never did nor would in that moſt excellent Author.</p>
            <p>If by Co-ordination, ſaith he, a Diviſion of Soveraignty be meant, it is againſt the nature of it, and a clear contradiction; ſo that, if the King be one Soveraign, there is no ſuch thing as Co-ordination; if three ſtates be joynt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, in what a miſerable condition are we Engliſh-men, who ſhould be bound to impoſſibilities, <hi>viz.</hi> three Maſters commanding contrary things? How can we do homage to any ſave him onely to whom we have ſworn, <hi>Cum per id efficiamur ſolius illius cui juravimus,</hi> as the Civilians determine, and we cannot be <hi>duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in ſolidum.</hi> They are his Subjects or not, if Subjects, not Co-ordinate; if not in ſubjection they <hi>ipſo facto</hi> put themſelves out of his protection, <hi>pag</hi> 88.</p>
            <p>And again, we grant, ſays that accute and learned Gentleman moſt truly, that there muſt be a joynt concurrence of three Eſtates to ſome purpoſes; ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:109337:14"/> making new and repealing old laws, raiſing ſupplies for the Kings neceſſities, in ſuch proportion as they ſhall think fitting, which are indeed great Democrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal advantages, yet the fruits of the moſt gracious conceſſions of our Princes, and therefore doubtleſs can include no authority of making Hoſtile reſiſtance againſt their Soveraign, in caſe he ſhould do contrary the to eſtabliſhed laws; 'tis true, they are in force, and bind the Conſcience, till abrogated by joynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but he cannot be forced to put them in execution, becauſe he hath no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour in juriſdiction; and no equall in managing <hi>jus gladii,</hi> or the material ſword, which is neceſſary to diſtinguiſh reſiſtance from rebellion, and give it the title of a juſt war. For, unleſs we can prove our ſelves not to be Subjects, if we fight we become Rebels by the Law of this Land, and by the Law of God incur a far greater penalty, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>pag.</hi> 139.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I have done with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s ſtanding <hi>next to God,</hi> and ſhall now come in the third place to ſpeak of <hi>Aaron</hi> ſtanding <hi>next to Moſes,</hi> or in ſubordination to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as I delivered it in the ſecond generall; and for this we have two very clear places of Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.1. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſee, I have made thee a god to</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and</hi> Aaron <hi>thy Brother ſhall be thy Prophet.</hi> And again, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>And he ſhall be thy ſpokeſman unto the people; he ſhall be, even he ſhall be to thee in ſtead of a Mouth, and thou ſhalt be to him in ſtead of a God.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> have a ſaying, that the Keys of the Temple were laid every night under <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Pillow, not hung to the High Prieſts girdle.</p>
            <p>Kings are doubtleſs Supreme in Spirituals alſo, yet Prieſts may do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things which Kings may not, though not without the Royal Aſſent and Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Then a King (ſays one) ſerves God like a King, when he does that for him which none elſe but a King can do, to maintain; ſettle and uphold religion by law is the great ſervice which belongs to a King. Let <hi>Moſes</hi> regulate the duties and ordinances pertaining to Divine Worſhip, but let <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons have the honour ſtill to Miniſter before the Lord. And indeed, we read not that <hi>Moſes</hi> medled with the Miniſtration of holy things after the Conſecration of <hi>Aaron:</hi> and we know how dear it coſt <hi>Saul</hi> his Sacrificing, and <hi>Uzziah</hi> his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe burning. We have this fully ſet forth in the example of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 Chron. 29.3, 4, 5. &amp;c. 3. <hi>He in the firſt Year of his raign in the firſt Month opened the doors of the Houſe of the Lord, and repaired them.</hi> 4. <hi>And brought in the Priests and the Levites, and gathered them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, into the Eaſt-ſtreet.</hi> 5. <hi>And ſaid unto them, hear me ye Levites, ſanctifie now your ſelves, and ſanctifie the Houſe of the Lord God of your Fathers, and carry forth the filthineſs out of the Holy Place.</hi> And then verſ. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. he goes on acknowledging the tranſgreſſions of their Fathers, and making a Covenat with God for turning away his fiery wrath. But verſe 11. he returns again to the Levites, <hi>My ſons be not now negligent: for the Lord
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109337:15"/> hath choſen you to ſtand before him, to ſerve him, and that you ſhould miniſter unto him, and burn incenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> here you ſee impowereth the Levites, but toucheth it not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; he commands, but they execute; he maketh proviſion for Religion, but medleth not with the action; he is Supreme as King, yet they act under him as Prieſts and Levites: And we are well aſſured alſo, that our ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thrive better, than when Kings are their nurſing fathers, and Queens their nurſing mothers, the influence of a Royal bounty being the moſt natural nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment for ſuch plants We are not for Civil Subjects, and Eccleſiaſtical Superiors, much leſſe are we for the ſetting up the Tripple Crown of <hi>Rome;</hi> we ſtand for, and ſtick to the Apoſtolical and Orthodox Doctrine of our 37th. Article, which ſeems to be myſtically ſet forth unto us, when the holy Crown was ſet upon the Miter in <hi>Aaron's</hi> Veſtments, <hi>Exod:</hi> 29.6. the one in ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, yet ſerviceable to the other; and then indeed the work went on, when <hi>Aaron</hi> led in his place as well as <hi>Moſes</hi> in his. When the Prince was a ſupport to the Prieſt, and the Prieſt to the Prince, then <hi>Amalek</hi> fell before the Armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed in <hi>Horeb,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> held up his arms.</p>
            <p>There were nevertheleſs of old, who thought the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> took too much upon them, as daily among us there ariſe men ſpeaking perverſe things, who would have perſwaded the world, that the claim of our ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> as from God, I mean our Epiſcopal Power, as from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, was an aſſault upon the right of our Kings, and tended to the diſheriſon of the Crown, as if, ſays<note n="*" place="margin">Learned Mr. <hi>Sancroft.</hi>
               </note> one of our own excellently, the Calling might not ſtand by divine right, and yet the Adjuncts and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendages by humane bounty.</p>
            <p>The Office it ſelf may ſurely be from Chriſt, and yet the exerciſe of it onely by and under the permiſſion of pious Kings. Why may not the Church owe the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, both that of Order and Juriſdiction too (purely ſpiritual, and without any temporal effect) to the Donation of Chri t, and yet at the ſame time owe all the coactive Power in the external Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, to the Political Sanction.</p>
            <p>Nor is this Diſcourſe impertinent either to the Text or Time; for as we have a <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo our <hi>Aarons</hi> alſo; and there is a very great Analogy betwixt theſe of the Old, and ours of the New Teſtament; thoſe by whom God led them to the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and theſe by whom he conducts to the new <hi>Jeruſalem. Aaron</hi> had a call from God, <hi>called as was Aaron, Heb.</hi> 5.4. the Prieſts that ſucceeded, ſucceeded in vertue of his call. We had Apoſtles, not by, or of men; and we have Apoſtolical men, reverend Fathers of the Church, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with power of Juriſdiction and Ordination, by vertue of that which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109337:15"/> Chriſt firſt placed in his Diſciples, yet acting in a profeſſed ſubjection to the Magiſtrates Super-inſpection, Regulation, and Cenſure. And now I hope you ſee, though it be by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that it is but <hi>by the Hand,</hi> not of either alone, but by the Hand of both; both are inſtrumental in order to this great mercy, both are employed by God, both are uſeful and neceſſary for his People; for without <hi>Moſes</hi> they would not have been a People, a Flock, but as ſheep ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on the Mountains of prey having no ſhepherd: and without <hi>Aaron,</hi> they would not have been Gods People. As men, we need <hi>Moſes;</hi> as Religious men, we need <hi>Aaron;</hi> and better be no Men, than not to be Religious Men; and to be no People, than not to be a Religious People. Both have but one work, both have but one hand, both being ſubordinate make up but one Agent, both are here Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioneo by God to bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt, Thou leddeſt by the hand, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Inconſiſtency, you ſee, <hi>Moſes</hi> may have the longeſt finger, though of the ſame hand, no jarring here. <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod, though it may devour the Rods of the Romiſh Sorcerers, that draw to the obedience of another Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head, yet not <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, and <hi>Aaron</hi> had a Rod too laid by the Pot of Manna; ſo alſo had St. <hi>Paul, Shall I come unto you with the Rod?</hi> the Rod of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline are very conſiſtent, yea, ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervient each to other.</p>
            <p>Nor may any wonder that we make Miniſtery to be full as high born a thing as Magiſtracy, that <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhould be extracted from as divine and heavenly a Pedigree as <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf; ſince they are Brethren, they may, I hope without offence, lawfully lay claim to the ſame Father. Now the ground of our Epiſcopacy is partly derived from the pattern preſcribed by God in the Old Teſtament, and partly from the imitation thereof confirmed by Chriſt himſelf, and brought in by the Apoſtles in the time of the New. The government of the Church of the old Teſtament was committed to the Prieſts and Levites, unto whom the Miniſters of the New do now ſucceed, in like ſort as our Lords day doth to their Sabbath, that it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophet touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vocation of the <hi>Gentiles, Iſa.</hi> 66.21. <hi>I will take of them for Prieſts, and for Levites, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Prieſts were ſuperior to the Levites, no man doubteth, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.6. and that there was not a parity either betwixt the Prieſts, or betwixt the Levites themſelves, is manifeſt by the Word of God, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 8.29. wherein mention is made of the Heads and Rulers both of the one and of the other.</p>
            <p>Each of the three Families of the Levites, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Gerſhonites,</hi> the <hi>Kobathites,</hi> and the <hi>Merarites</hi> had over them one <hi>Num.</hi> 24.30.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Ruler appointed by God himſelf; and as the Families of the Levites, ſo the four and twenty courſes of the Prieſts had their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, clearly diſtinguiſhed from that ſingular One, who was the Type of our great High Prieſt: Yea, in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109337:16"/> we find two of theſe named Biſhops in one Chapter, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 11. the one of the Prieſts, the other of the Levites, that dwelt in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the Greek Interpretation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. gives you among the Prieſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and both the Greek and Latine Interpreters <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. give you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Jerom</hi> renders, <hi>Epiſcopus Levitarum in Jeruſalem,</hi> Azzi <hi>filius Bani,</hi> and not without approbation of the Scripture it ſelf, which rendreth the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Original in the Old, by the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the New-Teſtament, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and his Biſhoprick let another take.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Epiſcopacy has its foundation in the Old-Teſtament, ſo it appears to be of Apoſtolical inſtitution alſo, for the prevention of Schiſm, and that upon the occaſion of thoſe notable Ones in the Church of <hi>Corinth: Beza</hi> himſelf hath done my work for me in theſe words, <hi>Certè ſi ab ipſis Apoſtolis eſſet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta haec mutatio non vererer illam ut ceteras Apoſtolicas ordinationes divinae in ſolidum diſpoſitioni tribuere.</hi> Sure I would not doubt (ſays he) to aſcribe to Epiſcopacy a divine Ordinance, if this change had proceeded from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walo, alias Salmaſius,</hi> the cruelleſt enemy ever Prelacy met with, will however ſo far gratifie us, <hi>Inſtitutio Epiſcopi ſi ab Apoſtolis eſt jure divino,</hi> If the inſtitution of Epiſcopacy be from the Apoſtles, then it is of divine right. That therefore which we have to do, is to prove it Apoſtolical, which we could do from Scripture Commented on by the conſtant practice of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and that again ſeconded by the Conceſſions of the moſt eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines of the Reformed Churches: But I had rather St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſhould do it for us, eſpecially ſince he of all the Antients is ſuppoſed leaſt to favour this cauſe; but let us hear him on <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antequam Diaboli inſtinctu, ſtudia in Religione fuerint diverſaria inter popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, Ego ſum Pauli, ego Apollinis, ego Cephae; communi conſilio Presbyteri Eccleſiae gubernabantur, poſtea autem toto terrarum Orbe decretum eſt, ut unus ex Presbyteris electus ſuperponeretur caeteris.</hi> Before, by the inſtinct of the devil, factions grew amongſt people in Religion, ſaying, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I of <hi>Apollo,</hi> I of <hi>Cephas;</hi> by common Councel the Churches were governed by Presbyters; but afterwards it was decreed through the world, that out of the Presbyters one ſhould be choſen and ſet over the reſt.</p>
            <p>The ground and occaſion of Epiſcopal Inſtitution you hear from this moſt learned Father, to have been thoſe Schiſmatical Rents and Diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> the time in which this healing Plaiſter was ſpread and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, was <hi>viventibus adhuc Apoſtolis,</hi> the Apoſtles being yet alive, as <hi>Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetus</hi> affirms, and no man can doubt, that will but read the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians.</hi> If then St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s authority paſs for currant, this is alone enough
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109337:16"/> to prove Epiſcopacy to be of Divine right, becauſe by Apoſtolical Inſtitution: And that this fell not from him by chance, but was his ſetled perſwaſion, is clear in that, beſides this paſſage, in the ninth Tome; we have in his firſt Tome a Catalogue of Eccleſiaſtical Writers, amongſt which he reckons up St. <hi>Peter,</hi> firſt Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> afterwards of <hi>Rome; James</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Juſtus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem, Timothy</hi> of <hi>Epheſus, Titus</hi> of <hi>Creet,</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with divers others; ſo antient is Epiſcopacy even according to <hi>Jerom.</hi> And again in his ſecond Tome, <hi>ad Rupert. adverſus Vigilant. miror ſanctum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum in cujus parochia Presbyter eſſe dicitur acquieſcere firmi ejus, &amp; non vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga Apoſtolica &amp; ferrea confringere vas inutile.</hi> Where the Epiſcopal part of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius,</hi> he calleth his Apoſtolical Iron Rod.</p>
            <p>And that we may prove all that we contend for, even from St. <hi>Jerom</hi> in the ſame Tome, inhis Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius, Quid non Presbyter facit, quod Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus excepta ordinatione,</hi> where he reſerves Ordination as the Biſhops pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar: And in the ſame Epiſtle we have theſe words alſo, <hi>Omnes Epiſcopi ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ſunt locorum, ſucceſſores ſunt Apoſtoli;</hi> All Biſhops are the Apoſtles ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. In the ſame place alſo alledging the Analogy between <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons, in reſpect of the Levites, with Biſhops and Presbyters, from, as he ſaith, Apoſtolical Tradition. It were incredible if all thoſe Apoſtolical relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, concerning Epiſcopacy, ſhould not amount unto ſo much as to make up an Apoſtolical Inſtitution, which if it does, it follows, it muſt be of Divine Ordinance, even the enemies being judges.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the ſecond General, on which I have inſiſted a little more than ordinary, as conſidering that we, our <hi>Moſes's</hi> and <hi>Aaron's,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Prieſts, have ſuffered ſo much by the disbelief of, and oppoſition to, theſe ſo great, ſo neceſſary Truths.</p>
            <p>And leſt any ſhould ſurmiſe, as the world is full of jealouſies and miſtakes, that I have all this while contended for tyrannical Oppreſſion, or inſolent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, to be exerciſed over thoſe who are quiet and harmleſs in the land, let me deſire your patience a little to the third and laſt particular, wherein is ſet forth the manner of Gods conducting <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> in the continuation of the Metaphor, <hi>as a Flock, i. e.</hi> with Lenity, and in Unity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With Lenity, like Sheep, not Swine or Oxen, with violence and rigour: And therefore when God choſe a man after his own heart to govern his people, He takes <hi>David from following the Ewes great with young, that he might feed Jacob his people, and Iſrael his Inheritance.</hi> And here <hi>Moſes</hi> a man of the ſame temper, the meekeſt man upon earth in his own concernments, but a Lion when Gods glory, or the good of the Church, required juſt ſeverity. We have a <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>David,</hi> one who ſhares in all thoſe endowments they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109337:17"/> were furniſhed with all, as they were to be Shepheards of Gods People; no <hi>Jehu, Phaeton,</hi> or <hi>Furius,</hi> one that hath that property of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> moſt eminently in him, that he is a mercifull King, he knows not how to puniſh but where 'twere cruelty to ſpare, where ſome tranſcendent villany hath left no room for mercy; this is a choyce Jewell in our Kings Crown, 'tis hard to ſay whether his Subjects love him more for his mercy and goodneſs, or his Enemies fear and dread him for his power and greatneſs; If yet he hath any Enemies, or if any fear him, ſure I am, they have no reaſon, unleſs they be ſuch as have rendred themſelves as uncapable of Gods mercy as of the Kings; now this will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and finall obſtinacy alone does. 'Tis not ſo much that we have been ſinners, as that we do perſiſt in ſin, ſuch an obſtinacy neither God nor his Vicegerent will endure, all the reſt is put in utter oblivion.</p>
            <p>Now for ſuch a Prince who deſires to have his Throne eſtabliſhed in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and ſupported with the Pillars of Mercy and Godlineſs, are we to pay the yearly tribute of Praiſes to our God this day, which I hope we ſhall all do with more enlargement of ſoul then ordinary. <hi>This is the Day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce and be glad in it:</hi> He hath made it a joyfull day for his Birth as a Man, a bleſſing to which Heaven bore witneſs in a Star appearing at Noon-day, as if nature it ſelf would teach us that there was a Sun and a Star, that might both very well ſhine together. Where was ever a Birth ſo atteſted, ſince that of our Saviour, will not eaſily be ſhewed? But this is not all, for as God hath made this a joyfull day for his being born as a Man, ſo alſo for being as it were born again as a Prince, in this deſired reſtitution to us his People, his Crown and Dignities; and that at ſuch a time, when his and his peoples enemies, were endevouring more ſolicitouſly then ever how to entail our miſery, and obſtruct every paſſage, which might bring us home ſuch a mercy. Now, <hi>praiſe the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me praiſe his holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing in Gods manner of Conduct was, that as it was with Lenity, ſo in Unity; as one ſheep, ſays the Original, one in reſpect of Union, a flock in reſpect of Communion and Society. Some ſtrayers from the flock there will be, and therefore Shepheards are neceſſary, and here let ſuch ſtrayers learn their own danger, and how to avoid it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by feeding with the flock; for though we read of a loſt ſheep, yet never of a whole flock, there is ſecurity doubtleſs as well as comfort in communion.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, as it diſpleaſeth God in Heaven, ſo it is no comfort to his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent here on Earth, to ſee his People ſcattered up and down in Holes and Hedge-bottomes, and ſtragling every one from their own Folds and Paſtures. He loves to ſee them as a flock.</p>
            <p>'Tis the intereſt of an Uſurper indeed, that there ſhould be Diviſion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the known Maxime, <hi>Divide et impera:</hi> But every Lawfull Prince
<pb facs="tcp:109337:17"/> with <hi>David</hi> would have their People as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a City compact within its ſelf: 'tis part of the work of this day to bleſſe the Name of God for a Prince wonderfully preſerved, reſtored and advanced to the Throne and Dignity of His Royal Predeceſſors, a Prince who by his Lenity hath invited and doth ſtill invite us unto Unity. O that his People would be like Gods People here, <hi>like a flock,</hi> and to that end, bleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od for reſtoring them again to the conduct of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of <hi>Aaron,</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> the King as Supreme, and be contented to be led by him, and thoſe that be ſent by him, <hi>i. e.</hi> governed and directed in the civil affairs of the Kingdome by the Civil Magiſtrate: By <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Biſhops and thoſe appointed by them in the ſacred things of God and his Church, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince ſelf-conceited fancy, and pretended revelation, and inſpiration by the Spirit, has experimentally been found to be the mother of all confuſion and deluſion.</p>
            <p>But ſince, to our knowledge, ſome among us are otherwiſe minded, I ſhall have ſomething to them by way of Application, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Here is ſomething by way of Redargution, and that to three ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as would willingly be led neither by <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as pretend highly to affect <hi>Moſes,</hi> but care not what becomes of <hi>Aaron;</hi> would be friends with the Crown, but are irreconcilably fallen out with the Mitre.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such as own both, love both, and would die for both in profeſſion, but diſgrace and diſhonour both by an unſuitable converſation. A word to each of theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some are neither for <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Aaron,</hi> a generat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of Seraphical men, as they count themſelves, which will be led by no other light; then the Candel of God within them; thoſe rays, which ſhining forth from the face of the Sun of Salvation are ſcattered upon their dark Souls, the only Piller they will have go before them all along the Wilderneſs, and theſe may well be ſtyled <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> being nothing elſe but the Spawns of thoſe old Prieſts who were poſſeſt by the Devil, or as they themſelves thought inſpired in their Fanes and from their Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; and then foming and raving they were wont ſo to put on God, as to put off men, uttering ſtrange things in their Extatical raptures, of which many oftentimes came to paſſe afterwards; a trick of the Devil's, thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them in the ways they were in, and inveigle others alſo: you have one of them deſcribed by <hi>Virgil,</hi> in the beginning of the ſixth of his <hi>Aeneids.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:109337:18"/>
               <l>— Non vultus, non color unus,</l>
               <l>Non Compcae manſere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: ſed pectus anhelum,</l>
               <l>Et rabic fera corda tument; majorque videri,</l>
               <l>Nec mortabo Sonans; afflata eſt numine quando.</l>
               <l>Jam propiore Dei. —</l>
            </q>
            <p>All which has in effect been already Engliſhed unto you, and therefore I ſhall ſpare that pains here. Theſe ſeem to be derived to us, from the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che's</hi> as thoſe from the <hi>Stoik's,</hi> the <hi>Stoik's</hi> held two principles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Mind and Matter. So the Manichees had their two principles which they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to be equally Eternall, Good and Evil. Good, they named Light and Mind; Evil, they call Darkneſs and Matter, which they thought the cauſe of all wickedne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and vice: men that acted upon the evil principle they ſtyled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Earthly and Material, whom they thought by reaſon of the ſeeds of their evil nature muſt neceſſarily be carried out to all manner of wickedneſs, and could not poſſibly turn themſelves or be turned unto God; on the contrary, thoſe who acted from Light or Mind, did neceſſarily do righteous things, and could not ſin, or walk in the broad way, by reaſon of the conduct of that light within them, though they taught alſo that they were not obnoxious to the law, though they brake it, becauſe the law was, ſaid they, for thoſe who from matter, were Material, not from ſpirit, Spiritual; they held that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we did, whether good or evil, we did it neceſſarily, and therefore reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both the Old and New-Teſtament, pretending to Revelations, Enthuſiaſmes, and Inſpirations, and that they might ſeem more then ordinary Mortals;<note n="*" place="margin">Car. Chron.</note> 
               <hi>Subito in turba ſe in terram abſicientes, &amp; velut attoniti, diu tacentes, deinde tanquam ex ſpecu Triphonio &amp; plorantes, multa vaticinati ſunt.</hi> On a ſuddain ſome of them falling down, and as it were aſtoniſhed or intranced, for a long time together not ſpeaking a word, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with a countenance as ſad and dejected, as if they came out of the Tripho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Den, they held forth, or uttered thoſe things which were revealed to them by the the Spirit in the Agony: Many of them were doubtleſs counterfeits, and (as wiſe men think) many alſo were really poſſeſt, that the Devil might the better carry on his deſign. Wedlock, Magiſtracy, Miniſtery, and all order, whether Political or Eccleſiaſtical; they held not to proceed from Light or Mind, but from the evil principle, Matter or Darkneſs. What horrid wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs this Party or Faction were guilty of, <hi>Clemens, Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> have recorded from the time of <hi>Marcion</hi> till this <hi>Colluvies Marcionis,</hi> this filth of <hi>Marcion</hi> ſeditiouſly ſeized <hi>Papuza in Phrygia,</hi> which they new Chriſtned <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> together with many other ſuch pranks acted over again by thoſe in <hi>Germany</hi> at <hi>Munſter,</hi> and by ſome amongſt us, who not many years
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109337:18"/> ſince Chriſtned <hi>Hamſhire</hi> by the name of the land of <hi>Ham,</hi> with much more to the ſame Tune. <hi>Manes</hi> at length pretending to heal diſeaſes alſo by a skill in Phyſick infuſed by the ſpirit, whether through ignorance or malice is doubtful, deſtroying the King of <hi>Perſiae</hi>'s Son whom he undertook to cure, was flayed alive, and ſo hung up againſt the Sun, and died miſerably. So let thine Enemies periſh, O Lord, and all thoſe which are the implacable adverſaries of thy <hi>Sion.</hi> Theſe, and ſuch as theſe, are indeed rightly termed Fanaticks: God forbid, that the ſober practiſes of honeſt and godly men and women, who make it their work to glorifie God, ſerving him in the Goſpel of his Son, &amp;c. to work out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling: I ſay again, God forbid, any ſuch ſhould be thus odiouſly branded, only, becauſe they run not into the ſame exceſs of riot with the wicked world. But let them have it, who deſerve it, by endevouring to overthrow all order in Church and State, and reduce us again to a Chaos of confuſion. 'Tis ſtrange there ſhould be any ſuch, yet that ſuch there have been, and ſtill are, is too evident; ſuch, I ſay as look upon all government as Tyranny, and juſt laws as Bolts and Shackles; ſuch as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Jude</hi> have charactered unto us in their Epiſtles, to deſpiſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, ſpeak evil of Dignities, and all preſumptuous and ſelf-willed perſons. It is doubtleſs true liberty to have the benefit of good Laws, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but right reaſon, and he's a Beaſt or Bedlame that will not be rul'd by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Theſe high-flown Chriſtians come ſhort of many of the old Pagans in this particular; ſo highly did the <hi>Perſians</hi> value their Laws, that they taught their Children the knowledge of them as ſoon as of letters. Others after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of great happineſs by obſerving old laws, and miſeries by indeavoring to innovate, would not indure a motion of any alteration,<note n="*" place="margin">Locrenſes.</note> but with Halters about their necks that made it, to the end they might preſently ſuffer, if their motion were not upon good grounds to be publickly approved of. The <hi>Grecians,</hi> and <hi>Agathyrſi,</hi> were ſo in love with their laws, that they taught them in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs with Muſick to their Children, an imitation poſſible of Gods own preſcription, who taught his people the ſumme of his Law in a Song. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives command that prayers, and not only prayers but thankſgivings alſo, ſhould be offered up to God for Kings and all in Authority, that under them we may live a godly and a peaceable life: if that we may, much more when we do, or may do if we pleaſe; let us make of it a day holy rejoycing upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count alſo, that this ſnare amongſt many other is broken, and our ſoul is eſcaped, ſince the Prince of the People has let us go free. 'Tis reported of one of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> houſes, that it was ſo infected with the Croking of Frogs, as that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt it became inhabitable and uſeleſs; which when <hi>Caeſar</hi> would go to ſee, the Frogs were ſilent ever after, and never heard to Croke more, when he had once appeared there. <hi>Caeſar</hi> has appeared, and we partly have, and partly hope
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109337:19"/> the like effects through the Nation; for thoſe crokers which have ſo long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected us, either Croke faintly, or are quite ſilenced in many other places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others there are who forſooth ptetend they ſhould like the King, could they but keep the Biſhop from putting in his foot: But we know that the ſame principles, and perhaps arguments too, which trample upon the Mitre, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane the Crown alſo, and caſt it to the ground. 'Tis ſtrange thoſe men ſhould cry out againſt Hereſie and Schiſme, no men more or louder, and yet pull down with their own hands the beſt fence, and mount that ever the Church experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented againſt both. But we are now come to grant a Primitive Epiſcopacy; to this, as has been prov'd belongs Juriſdiction and Ordination, and who ever pretended to, or contended for more? T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir Mannors, Lordſhips and other Perquiſites and Appurtenances, they acknowledge they owe to he favour of Princes, and we affirm they may be or may not be, the eſſence of a Biſhop re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining intire without them. Yet why only learned men ſhould eſpouſe Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, and when men place abroad their Children to other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ades, why ſhould they have an eye to their future advancement, and riſing to wealth and honour in the world, and yet doom ſuch of them as with more care and coſt they bring up to learning, I ſay, to doom to ſuch to poverty and raggs, is not eaſily imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Is it rational of Scholars only, many of which would have come to as much in any other way, as any other men, ſhould be bound to take upon them the moſt laborious calling in the world, and ſtudy hard for many years, only that at length they may become poor and contemptible? I believe if we ſhould ſet down and ſoberly debate the buſineſs, there would be as good reaſon ſhewn, why there ſhould be parity amongſt all other men alſo, as there can, why there ſhould be amongſt Scholars and Church-men. But to paſs by theſe men and their irrational principles, I hope we have not ſo learned Chriſt and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but that with joy and gladneſs we own <hi>Aaron</hi> as well as <hi>Moſes;</hi> nor ought it to be forgotten this day, ſince 'tis a day of Remembrance, that with our Ancient Monarchy God has been pleaſed graciouſly to reſtore our Ancient Primitive, Apoſtolical Epiſcopacy; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od has put it into the Kings heart to mind the Houſe of God more then his own, is, and ought be the cauſe of many Thankſgivings, to as many as have a good will to this our <hi>Sion</hi> this day; nor let that vulgar objection prevail with you, <hi>that you would be for good Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops:</hi> You acknowledge, I am ſure, that you have no reaſon to complain, you I mean of this City and Dioceſs, but to bleſs God this day upon that account al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, and therefore you are bound to judge charitably of all the reſt of theſe Reverend Fathers of the Church by what you have ſeen with comfort in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is a word of ſevere reproof for ſuch as own both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in profeſſion, but diſhonour both, or any Cauſe they adhere to, by an unſuitable
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109337:19"/> life and converſation. We hope the world is a little better inſtructed, than to judge of principles by ſome particular mens practiſes; for we confeſs with grief of heart, that there are a Rabble in the world that pretend to be for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> which the true ſons of the Church do heartily wiſh were of any other perſwaſion. Men and women, under the burden of whoſe ſins the beſt Cauſe that ever was in the world has ſunk once already, and we may juſtly fear will, without ſpeedy repentance and amendment, pull down freſh judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon us again;, I mean, ſuch who live, as if to be lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al were to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, and there were no may of manifeſting our affection to our King, but by drinking his Health; 'tis to be fear'd they have to anſwer for drinking one King dead already, thus mingling Royal blood with their wine. For, <hi>Let the Throne of my Lord the King be for ever clear;</hi> we muſt take to our ſelves the guilt of thoſe ſins, which gave the ſaddeſt ſtroke that ever was ſtruck in the world. Nor can there be a greater diſhonor to our preſent Soveraign, than to make preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of affection towards him, the ſhelter and ſanctuary for looſneſs and all manner of debauchery; then to part aſunder what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od hath joyned together, <hi>viz. Fear God,</hi> from <hi>Honour the King.</hi> And I wiſh all thoſe who ſpend moſt of their time in ſuch looſe, diſſolute, and debauched practiſes, would lay this to heart; ſuch, I ſay, who have ſcarce time through the year to entertain a ſerious thought, but live as if God had ſent them into the world, as the <hi>Leviathan</hi> into the deep, onely to take their paſtime there; thoſe are they who for the moſt part ſcoffe at Sermons, and are never ſo witty as in their Atheiſtical contempt of all Miniſtery; let them pretend what they pleaſe, they love no Miniſter that will deal roundly and plainly with them. And here I cannot but condole the ſad condition of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Papiſts will kiſs the hem of the meaneſt Friars garment; Schiſmaticks adore their ſeducing Ring-lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and would even pull out their own eyes to do them good: onely ſome men who would be counted true Proteſtants, but indeed are down-right Atheiſts, ſpeak reproachfully of, and deal mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſcornfully and imperiouſly with as learned a Clergy, as excellent a Miniſtery, as ever the Church enjoyed. For I have experimentally found, that through the ſides of Factio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Schiſmatical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des, they wound all the reſt. How can they bleſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od this day for them, that think, and ſtick not to ſay, it would be better without them. God grant this do concern none that hear me this day, I hope it does not, any farther than to enlarge your hearts in thankfulneſs, as for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of Monarchy, ſo the eſtabliſhing of Miniſtery; which had ere this been utterly deſtroyed, had not God wonderfully interpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the wiſdom, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and integrity of his Excellency, our moſt renowned General, betwixt us and the ſad things deſigned for us.</p>
            <p>We can expreſs our thankfulneſs no way better, than by living worthy ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109337:20"/> great mercies and gracious deliverances; eſpecially let us be careful of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting a hatred and abhorrency of thoſe ſins, which had a moſt immediate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into our puniſhment; yea, which God turned into puniſhments. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that whilſt the Nation ceaſed to be Loyal, they were Miſerable; that ever ſince the Kings Throne was caſt to the ground, God has been pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out contempt upon us alſo, yea, upon the whole Nation, even to the time of his Majeſty's Reſtitution. Yea, let our prayers be for our <hi>Jeruſalem, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> of old was <hi>Domus Regni &amp; Religionis,</hi> there were the Thrones of the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and there were the Ark and the Tabernacle; let us therefore joyn, Church and State, King and Prieſt, in our duties this day; when we pray to, and praiſe God for <hi>Moſes,</hi> let not <hi>Aaron</hi> be forgotten; ſo ſhall <hi>peace be within our walls, and plenteouſneſs within our palaces; God ſhall bleſs us out of Sion,</hi> yea, God ſhall bleſs us out of Heaven, delighting ſtill to <hi>lead us as a flock by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Here's a word of Exhortation, and that to ſeveral Duties.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſit down and recount with our ſelves, how wonderfully God hath appeared for us, breaking our <hi>Egyptian</hi> yoke, and reſtoring <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to us, and us to them: Here to ſet in order before you thoſe <hi>Magnalia Dei,</hi> thoſe wonders of the moſt High, were the work rather of a Chronicle than a Sermon; yet, for method's ſake, conſider the deliverance God hath wrought, and the alterations by which he hath compaſſed them. Firſt, for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, he took us as a prey out of the jaws of the terrible, and broke every ſtaffe of the oppreſſor in pieces. Neither was this deliverance onely from what was felt, but what was feared; what had been continued was bad, but that which was now upon the wheel, when God broke them in pieces, was yet worſe, if worſe could be.</p>
            <p>But now let us ſee what it coſt ere <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would let the People go free; and firſt it coſt the removing one that was a terror in the land of the living, and laid his ſword under his head; the cauſe of all that miſery theſe poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions felt for twelve years together was removed in a moment, God taking that quarrel into his own hand, and ſummoning him to anſwer before a higher Court of Juſtice than ever he erected. 2. It coſt the diſcovering of the greateſt hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, diſſemblers, and ſelf-ended publick pretenders that ever were in the world. 3. It coſt the defeating of many <hi>Achitophels,</hi> and turning the wiſdom of the wiſeſt into folly. The caſe of our Soveraign is ſet forth <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33, 34. and that of his and our enemies is ſet forth alſo, if you compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.16, 17. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſtudy our own mercy and duty, conſider what God has beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, for what he removed from us. That which we have received from him is the greateſt token of his love, even the Signet of his own right hand; he has
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109337:20"/> fulfilled the ſame promiſe to us which he made to his people of old, after their return from captivity, <hi>Haeg.</hi> 2.23. in giving <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the ſon of <hi>Shealtiel,</hi> in reſtoring one lineally deſcended from our antient Monarchs, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right it was. Four things, ſome ſay, muſt not be in a Signet, it muſt not have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an idolatrous ſtamp or ſculpture; and ſurely in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> is a fit Signet for Gods own right hand, he neither names, knows, nor worſhips any other, ſave the God of his fathers; which will ſeem the more admirable, if we conſider his age, and the advantages he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably have made by changing his Religion. But neither the wicked and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable practiſes of theſe his enemies, who pretended to the ſame Religion, nor the complying overtures from the Factors of <hi>Rome,</hi> could ever bring him to bow in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon;</hi> thereby making it appear, that it was his ſetled perſwaſion, that he were far better ſit down by the loſſe of three earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, than hazard his Title to one heavenly Crown.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There muſt not be cut or engraven on it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an inſtrument of cruelty. Our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> has no other but a ſtamp of clemency, and therefore in this reſpect alſo fit for a Signet to be worn on Gods own right hand, he never does any thing with a worſe mind than puniſh, wiſhing really, <hi>utinam neſcirem literas,</hi> when he is forced to ſign a fatall Bill or Warrant, but where 'twere cruelty to ſpare, where tranſcendent villany has left no room for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or mercy. So that though all men acknowledge him to be admirable at remembring men, yet muſt it be confeſt, that he is far better at forgetting injuries.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt not have on it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. an emblem of intemperance. Our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> bears no other but the ſtamp of ſobriety, he has throughly learn'd <hi>Lemuel</hi>'s mothers leſſon, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.4. <hi>It is not for Kings, O Lemuel, it is not for Kings to drink wine, nor for Princes ſtrong drink.</hi> He is far from the diſeaſe of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> complains of, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.16, 17. <hi>He eats and drinks for health and ſtrength, not for exceſs and drunkenneſs;</hi> yea, ſo far is he from this, that ſome who were habitual drunkards, as we have heard have been ſtrangely reclaimed, ſince they perceived that they could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſure of their ſin, without the diſpleaſure of their Soveraign. And therefore in this reſpect alſo is our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> a Signet fit for Gods own right hand.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Signet may not have on it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a wanton or a laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious Poſey. Our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> bears no other but a ſtamp of chaſtity, take all circumſtances even to a miracle; Whoſe bed hath he defiled? whoſe Virgin hath he defloured? had he been blemiſh'd but with the leaſt ſuſpition in this kind, time was when it would have been ſufficiently aggravated: But bleſſed be the God of that grace, which has kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him in this reſpect as well as in all others:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109337:21"/> So that he has perfectly learnt that good old leſſon, <hi>Regium eſt ita vivere, ut non modo hominum nemini, ſed ne libidini ſerviant:</hi> ſurvey the world, and not many ſuch men; ſurely not ſuch a King again to be found. And therefore in this reſpect alſo is our <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> a fit Signet for Gods own right hand. To proſecute this a little further, if any remain yet unconvinced, if any have the heart to look back upon, and hanker after the fruit of their ways, who have not periſhed, as they deſerved, <hi>in the gain-ſaying of Corah;</hi> let them but conſider the difficulty of the work they have to do, and then <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, and do their own buſineſs;</hi> if ever they prevail, they muſt pluck Gods Signet from him, to which the Scripture has aſſigned three places, all importing the Signets ſafety.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The right hand, as in the ſecond of <hi>Haggai,</hi> the laſt before cited, and this implies <hi>cuſtodia dextrae,</hi> the protection of his right hand, for them who are the men of his right hand, as Kings are ſtyled; this, I ſay, implies ordinary preſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are Extraordinary caſes of danger, and therefore he hath a ſtronger place; His Arm, a Signet on his arm, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. God hath a ſtrong arm, an out-ſtretched arm, an arm of ſalvation for extraordinary dangers. This Signet of his has had ſufficient experience of the hand, yea, and of the out-ſtretched arm of his God too, for his defence in times of greateſt danger.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He hath yet a cloſer and ſurer place to ſet his Signet on, and that is on his Heart, in the place laſt cited, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. and this betokens the greateſt care and cuſtody; the Heart is called <hi>Repoſitorium amoris,</hi> Love's Cabinet. Now <hi>Love is ſtrong as death,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon.</hi> There is then a Hand to hold Gods Signet, an arm to defend it, and a heart for his hiding place: It will be hard to ſnatch him out of his Hand, harder out of his Arm, but hardeſt out of his heart. Lay aſide therefore your thoughts of revenge, and take up thoughts of praiſes this day, and that ſhall be the third Branch of my Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be exhorted to conſider what Gods deſign may be in all the great things he hath done for, and amongſt us; yea, in beſtowing the Signet of his own right Hand, Arm, and Heart upon us; ſurely his main end is his own own glory, the carrying on of Chriſts Kingdom, by removing what ever ſtands in its way. We have heard much talking in theſe laſt days of the Kingdom and Scepter of Jeſus Chriſt; if any Government in the world may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to theſe Titles above the reſt, it is doubtleſs that antient way by Biſhops and Archbiſhops, which theſe expreſſions have been made uſe of to pull down, which Chriſt himſelf bears witneſs unto, by removing what ever ſtands in its way; <hi>Covenants, Congregations, Anabaptiſts, Quakers,</hi> whatſoever op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth out Articles, Liturgy, and Epiſcopacy, is born down before it,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109337:21"/> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.32. <hi>What ſhall one anſwer the meſſengers of the Nation? the Lord hath founded this our</hi> Sion, <hi>the poor of the Nation ſhall trust in it.</hi> Gods deſign you ſee is founding <hi>Sion,</hi> raiſing a Phaenix out of her Aſhes, making that which was but Brick to be Marble, and turning Sicamore into Cedar.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be exhorted to anſwer all his mercies with ſuitable returns, as he hath preſerved the Goſpel, ſo let us adorn it, as we do now again enjoy Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, ſo let us get Holy Hearts; Heavenly Inſtitutions will but aggravate our condemnation if we be without Heavenly Converſations. We had need be the more carefull in this particular, becauſe no temptation is ſo ſtrong under mercy as to break off Communion with God; the Devils yoke being ſhaken off he would fain revenge himſelf by cauſing you to ſhake off Chriſt Yoke alſo; but if you would complete your mercies, ſet your Faces againſt your ſins, ſhew that you Honour the King by fearing God. Our ſins drew down a heavy ſtorm on the Father, for ſtill we muſt acquit the Throne, and condemn our ſelves, let our repentance procure bleſſings for the Son our Soveraign; for know this, that if judgement be removed and ſin remains, it is removed in anger, not in mercy, God gives over puniſhing in diſpleaſure. It may go, but it is <hi>Cum animo revertendi,</hi> it goes to return again, if we take not Chriſts warning, <hi>Go and ſin no more,</hi> a worſe thing will befall us; if we do exalt our ſelves, God will plead with us; if we turn his grace into wantonn ſs, then his anger in ſmiting ſhall not be turned away, <hi>But his hand ſhall be ſtretched out ſtill:</hi> That therefore he may not be provoked to withdraw theſe rich expreſſions of his loving kindne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in diſpleaſure, Give him in theſe three returns eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give him a return of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, magnifie that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od who hath ſweetned all your ſufferings with ſo gracious a deliverance; God expects this tribute from his redeemed ones, <hi>Call upon me ſays God in the day of trouble, I will deliver thee, and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalt glorifie me,</hi> Iſa. 65.13, 14. there be the King and Countries friends diſtinguiſhed from others by their joy and thankfulneſs on ſuch a day. <hi>Behold, my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſhamed; behold, my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houl for vexation of ſpirit.</hi> We are called this day as many as have a good will to King and Kingdome, to Sing the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Lamb; of <hi>Moſes</hi> for Temporal, and the Lamb for Spiritual delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; if ever a Nation in the world had cauſe, we have to ſing it this day, we are led from <hi>Egypt</hi> for Slavery, from <hi>Babel</hi> for Diſorder and Confuſion, from a meer Hell for Hereſie and Blaſphemy. <hi>Egypt</hi> began to double the tale, and now God reſolved to free his People from making the Bricks; be not backward then, ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Lamb, ſpeak thanks and live thanks.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Give him in a return of Worſhip and of Service, teſtifie your thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109337:22"/> by a conſtant attendance on his worſhip, when his People of old would go out of <hi>Egypt</hi> they had no other pretence but that they might Sacrifice to their God. You pretend you value the Liturgy, and remember the reſtitution of it as a great mercy this day, be conſtant therefore henceforth in waiting upon God in that Service, and ſhew that you value it by abandoning the ſins there prayed againſt, by improving the grace, and following the conducts of that ſpirit there pray'd for and to, by being moved with the exhortations, and dreading the comminations of that book. This is the uſe we ſhould make of ſuch a deliverance, that being delivered from the hands of our enemies, we may ſerve him without fear; if we improve not mercies this way, God will ſay of us as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Nabal, Surely in vain have I kept theſe men, and all that they have.</hi> 1 Sam. 25.21. <hi>They have requited me evil for good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Give him a return of holineſs, let us teſtifie that God leads us by being godly, and make it appear that Loyalty is very conſiſtent with Piety, and that the beſt Chriſtians are alſo the beſt Subjects. His preſence among them was the great argument from which he preſſed his People of old. O that his Spirit would bring forth this fruit of theſe his gratious dealings, that we might be a holy peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le: let us take care of proſtituting ſuch mercies to the ſervice of any luſts whatſoever. Beware o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> making that uſe of peace and plenty that the rich fool in the Goſpel does, <hi>Soul take thine eaſe,</hi> follow Luxury, Pride and Vanity, let not thoſe that are or have been Filthy, Profane and Looſe, be ſo ſtill, let every one forſake his evil way, and the iniquity that is in his hand. That we who erewhile were ſcarce a People, may now be a People to the praiſe of the God of our mercies, that God may look upon our Soveraign for good, and that as he is, ſo he may continue as the light of the morning when the Sun is riſen, even as a morning without clouds, and that we who are under rule, may every man ſet under our own Vine, and under our own Figtree, and praiſe the God of peace in peace.</p>
            <p>Send us away at preſent with ſuch apprehenſions as theſe upon our ſpirits. God hath ſo done his Miraculous works, that they ought to be had in everlaſting remembrance, and endevour to lay the due Emphaſis not ſo much on the things done, as on the doer of them; not ſo much on this that they are done, as that you can read God in them. <hi>Our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird, the Snare is broken, and we are eſaped.</hi> And then to cloſe up all, <hi>What ſhall I render to God for all this? I will take the cup of Salvation, and I will pay my vows</hi> of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, of worſhip and ſervice, yea, of holineſs unto the Lord, for leading <hi>us as a flock</hi> from <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan, by the hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and of</hi> Aaron.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:22"/>
            <head>Books newly Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Thrale,</hi> at the <hi>Croſs-Keys</hi> at St. <hi>Paul's Gate,</hi> entring into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ECcleſiae Anglicanae</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in qua perturbatiſſimus Regni &amp; Eccleſiae ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſub Anabaptiſtica Tyrannide, lugetur. Dictante</hi> Johanne Gough <hi>S. Th. D. Coll. B.</hi> Ma. Magd. Oxon. <hi>quondam Socio, Vicariae</hi> S<hi rend="sup">ti.</hi> Stephani <hi>juxta</hi> Cantuariam <hi>nuperrime reſtituto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Moſt accurate Hiſtory of the ancient City, and famous Cathedral of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, being an exact deſcription of all the Rarities in that City, Suburbs and Cathedral; together with the Lives of all the Arch-biſhops of that See, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated with divers Maps and Figures; publiſhed by <hi>William Sumner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Breviate of our King's whole Latine Grammer, vulgarly called <hi>Lillies,</hi> (analytically diſpoſed) or a brief Grammatical Table thereof, to facilitate the Apprehenſion, ſtrengthen the Memory, and to encreaſe the benefit of young Learners, made for the uſe of all Philologiſts; by the labour and pains of <hi>Joſh. Brookbank</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mancheſter al Mondo. Contemplatio Mortis &amp; Immortalitatis.</hi> A Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Death and Immortality. The ſeventh Impreſſion much enlarged, with the Latine Sentences rendred into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Mirror which flatters not, concerning the Contempt of the World;</hi> or, <hi>the Meditations of Death</hi> of <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon, Saladine, Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great: by <hi>le Sieur de la Serre</hi> Hiſtoriographer of <hi>France,</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed into <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the <hi>French</hi> by <hi>T. Cary</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Antidote againſt immoderate ſorrow for the death of our friends,</hi> taken from an aſſured hope of our Reſurrection to Life and Glory. Delivered in a Sermon preached in the Pariſh Church of <hi>North-wraxal</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> the 12 of <hi>April</hi> 1660. at the Funeral of Sir <hi>William Button</hi> Baronet; by <hi>Francis Baily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſtrong man ejected by a ſtronger than he:</hi> In a Sermon preached at <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter May</hi> 15. 1660, being the day his Royal Majeſty King <hi>Charls</hi> the Second was proclaimed. By <hi>W. Bartholomew</hi> M. A. Vicar of <hi>Campden</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon prepared to be preached at the Funeral of <hi>Walter Norbane</hi> Eſq; by <hi>William Haywood</hi> D. D. and one of the Chaplains in Ordinary to his late Majeſty of glorious memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virgilii Evangeliſantis Chriſtiados Libri</hi> 13. <hi>in quibus omnia quae de Domino nostro Jeſu Chriſto in utroque Teſtamento, vel dicta vel praedicta ſunt, altiſona divina Maronis tuba ſuaviſſime decantantur, inflante</hi> Alexandro Roſſeo <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109337:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Carminum Proverbialium totius humanae vitae ſtatum breviter delinea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> nec non utilem de moribus doctrinam jucunde proponentium. Loci communes in gratiam juventutis ſelecti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The works of that famous Phyſician D. <hi>Alexander Read,</hi> Dr. of Phyſick, and one of the Fellows of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Colledge <hi>London;</hi> containing Chyrurgical Lectures of Tumors and Ulcers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Treatiſe of the firſt part of Chyrurgery, which teacheth the reunitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the parts of the Body disjoyn'd, and the methodical doctrine of Wounds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Treatiſe of all the Muſcles of the body of Man.</p>
            <p>The Manuel of the Anatomy of the body of Man, containing the Enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Deſcription of the parts of the ſame, which uſually are ſhewed in the publick Anatomical Exerciſes, with ſundry Figures; by Dr. <hi>Alexander Read.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Compleat Gentleman,</hi> faſhioning him abſolute in the moſt neceſſary and commendable Qualities, concerning Mind or Body, that may be required in a Perſon of Honor; with the Gentlemans Exerciſe for Drawing, Limming, Painting, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thearrum Botanicum,</hi> A Theater of Plants, or a compleat univerſal Herbal; by <hi>John Perkinſon,</hi> in Folio.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paradici in ſoli Paradiſus terreſtis,</hi> or a Garden of all ſorts of the rareſt Flowers, with their nature, place of birth, time of flowering, uſeful in Phyſick, or admired for beauty: To which is added a Kitchen-Garden, furniſhed with all manner of Fruits, and Roots, and Herbs, uſed with us for Meat or Sauce. Alſo the Art of pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting an Orchard; with the right way of Preſerving and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of them, with their ſelect Vertues; by <hi>John Perkinſon,</hi> in Folio.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
